<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The golden fleece. VVherein is related the riches of English wools in its manufactures Together with the true uses, and the abuses of the aulnageors, measurers, and searchers offices. By W. S. Gent.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4255CA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221504</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832802</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832802</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37276</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60593)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37276)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2060:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The golden fleece. VVherein is related the riches of English wools in its manufactures Together with the true uses, and the abuses of the aulnageors, measurers, and searchers offices. By W. S. Gent.</title>
                  <author>Smith, W., gent., attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.G. for Richard Lowndes, at the white Lyon in S. Pauls Church-yard, neere the Little north-doore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing attributes this to W. Smith.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; pages cropped, stained, with print show-through with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wool industry --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37276:1"/>
            <p>THE Golden Fleece. VVherein is related the Riches of <hi>Engliſh Wools</hi> in its Manufactures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together with</hi> The true Uſes, and the Abuſes of the <hi>Aulnageors, Meaſurers,</hi> and <hi>Searchers</hi> Offices.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. S.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pecunia à Pecude.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Guic. Plin. lib. 33.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Omnes veterum divitiae in re pecuniari â conſiſtebant.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>Richard Lowndes,</hi> at the white Lyon in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, neere the Little North-doore. 1657.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37276:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37276:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37276:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37276:3"/>
            <head>A Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THere is neither Houſe, nor City, nor Country, nor the univerſall Being of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, nor the courſe of Nature, nor the World it ſelfe, which can ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without Government, ſaith <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> in his Diſcourſe upon Lawes; which Government intends and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes theſe two Fundamentals or corner ſtones, <hi>Povver</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> by which as the Regiment of every Common-wealth doth ſtand, ſo the flouriſhing Trade of <hi>England</hi> (under Societies and Companies) doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt the ſame to the whole world: Nevertheleſſe, as in generall
<pb facs="tcp:37276:4"/>all men cry up Liberty, ſo in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular each reſpective man deſires that freedome <hi>gratis,</hi> though it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be granted without thoſe contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary ſervices which maintain that Government. The Seas exhale their Vapours to the Heavens, from whence they deſcend in Showers upon the earth, which being impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by their fertility, doth grateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſmiſſe them again to the Ocean, Natures Store-houſe for the like courſary ſervices; <hi>Alterius ſic altera poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit opem, et conjurat amice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The regulated government of Merchandice performeth all this, by which it beautifies the Earth and Seas, giving intercourſe and combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſupplies and riches to each induſtrious part of the world; It
<pb facs="tcp:37276:4"/>procures Amities, Leagues, Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracies, Conjugall and Conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Alliances between Princes, and all by the neceſſary productions which one Nation wants of anothers abundance, the purchaſe whereof to each others occaſions nouriſheth and beautifies each others People. How then ſhould not Merchants be of principall renowne to themſelves and their Country, which with great hazards both of perſon and eſtate, they do ſo faithfully and profitably ſerve.</p>
            <p>We have a Record which doth worthily recite the ingenious expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a young <hi>Florentine</hi> Gentleman called <hi>Coſimo Ruchelli,</hi> who dying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the age of two and twenty years bewayled not his departure from his
<pb facs="tcp:37276:5"/>Kindred and Friends, nor from the riches of his Family, or pleaſures of the world, but becauſe he was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by Death before he had done his Country that retributary ſervice which to it was due for his Being, or had gratified his Friends by reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall benefits for that they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon him, nouriſhment and education. Another Author gives us a quite contrary opinion of one <hi>Theodorus,</hi> who thought, and taught it to be great injuſtice, that a wiſe man ſhould in any caſe hazard him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for the good or benefit of his Country, which he ſaid was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger his wiſdome for Fooles; now though each of theſe mens fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies had a rationall foundation upon their reſpective principles, one to
<pb facs="tcp:37276:5"/>gratify and ſerve the world, the other to deſpiſe and reject its vanities, yet Natures poſitive doctrine to all her Children, is, <hi>Non nobis ſolum nati ſumus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God made the world in number, weight, and meaſure, becauſe he would have it ſo preſerved, and by that Preſident he appointed man to govern both it and himſelfe; for as in Order there is beauty and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, each part in its proportion ſo ſupporting another as with comlines it hath durance; ſo in government amongſt men, that which we call Juſtice, is in its diſtribution the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſervation of the whole which it intends to govern, and that is, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte vivere, alterum non laedere, ſuum cui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tribuere;</hi> and this is the worke of
<pb facs="tcp:37276:6"/>every honeſt and wiſe man, ſo it is to follow the primitive un-erring pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of Number, Weight, and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which was obſerved by God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prima ſapientiae pars eſt bene numerare,</hi> ſaith <hi>Plato,</hi> and well to number a mans dayes is the ready way to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſaith <hi>David:</hi> both theſe were excellent Divines, though not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives, yet without numbers we cannot ſo diſtinguiſh, but that <hi>Plato's</hi> heathen may claim as great eſteeme as <hi>Davids</hi> heavenly wiſdome; this gives to one the moſt excelling fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and to the other the ſuper-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent infinite meaſure of his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; one of them fulfilling the firſt of the morall, and the other of the divine Vertues, and from theſe
<pb facs="tcp:37276:6"/>the equality of meaſuring between men, takes being, and is the life-blood of Trade.</p>
            <p>As without a common certainty of meaſure there can be no inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, nor tranſaction of trade be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men or Nations, ſo in this of Clothing, <hi>(The glory of England)</hi> there can be no indifferency, rule, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, without ſuch an eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of meaſure and proportion as may ſatisfy every man in his bargain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, bartering, buying, or exchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In the following diſcourſe will appeare a great deviaton from the determined rules of Juſtiice provided in this caſe, and ſuch a neceſsity of reformation, as Clothing cannot be freed from open or underhand abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes without it; nor can this peculia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed
<pb facs="tcp:37276:7"/>bleſſing of Woolls in its ſtreames of Manufacture anſwer to the cleareneſs of the fountaine from whence it ſprings.</p>
            <p>There are now a Trinity of offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers relating to the regulation of Clothing, all which were anciently compriſed in the Vnity of one mans perſon; theſe beare the diſtinct names of Searcher, Meaſurer, and Aulna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geor, which laſt, though it be a tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tologicall expreſsion (Aulnage and Meaſure being the ſame worke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted in two languages) yet the long vſage and cuſtome have brought them to be diſtinct offices, and that which anciently was called Aulnage, from whence the Aulnageor takes his name, who was no more but meaſurer in ſignification, is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb facs="tcp:37276:7"/>Collector of the Subſidy gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the State, by many preciſe Laws in that caſe ordained, ſtill holding the name of Aulnageor, becauſe the collection of that Subſidy was by King Edward 3. committed to the charge of the Aulnageor, and he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe not abridged of his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring and ſearching, till by his own wilfull neglect they became ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that by diſtinct Lawes; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as there is a peculiar Meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, who ought to know, and allow the Aſſize of length and breadth to every Particular Cloth which is made in England and Wales: And becauſe the Subjects of this Land ſhould not be abuſed, their grave Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators in Parliaments have alſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed an office of ſearching, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:37276:8"/>Officer ought by his Seales (judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and diligently affixed) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the defaults, and caſuall abuſes which each particular Cloth doth contain.</p>
            <p>In the following diſcourſe it will appeare, that theſe offices were all of them under the cognizance of the <hi>Aulnageor,</hi> &amp; until they ſhall be again reſtored unto his care, and that he be as well under ſtrict termes obliged, as by competent Salaries enabled to ſee the duty diſcharged, Clothing in England will be ſo farre ſhort of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering its priſtine worth, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as it will undoubtedly run ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to decay, &amp; through neceſſity the materials (now forbiden to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported under the penalty of life and limb) muſt be licenced to go to ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:37276:8"/>places, as will more juſtly diſcharge the manufactures, and then will be found the irrecoverable want of thoſe two great bleſſings, which our Anceſtors ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to increaſe, which are <hi>Wealth</hi> in generall, and <hi>Strength</hi> in numbers of People, both of which have within theſe laſt 300. yeares ſo multiplyed under the Monarchs of England, as by the Trade of Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing they have been loved or feared of all Nations.</p>
            <p>How thoſe Officers ſtand now directed by the Lawes, and how unable the people therein employed are to diſcharge thoſe duties, will in the following worke be found to be expreſsly and according to the Lawes delivered; Inſomuch as every man
<pb facs="tcp:37276:9"/>of judgment who will vouchſafe to read the relation, will by his naturall affection to his Country, be induced to endeavour a timely reformation; leſt as the moſt illuminating Tapers of Religion and Learning, are through the provocations of a ſinful People whelm'd under a Buſhell of Obſtinacy and Ignorance, ſo the Riches and Glories of this Lands peculiarized endowments in <hi>wooll</hi> and <hi>clothing,</hi> will not ſo much be carried away by an invading enemy, as forced to be tranſplanted by its own People, who dayly worke ſo induſtriouſly in that Mine, as a very ſhort time will bring the Stranger under the Walles of our ſafety, which God forbid, and whereto every true Engliſh-man will ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37276:9"/>
            <head>THE GOLDEN FLEECE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>About Wooll and Clothing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing in this flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nation of <hi>England</hi> ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally good, and beneficial to the people thereof, as is the converſion of <hi>Wooll</hi> into its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Manufactures, wherein it anſwers the Invention of Man; the conſequences where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of relate as well to the Soveriegn, as to the ſubject, to the Noble as well as to the Ignoble, compriſing all conditions of men, women, and children. For as in Man the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37276:10"/>Brain and Liver aſſiſting the Heart do no more but preſerve themſelves, and are chief in their own contemplation, though they ſeem onely to complement, and attend the Heart; and as the peoples readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to obey doth ſeem to ingratiate them to their ſupreme powers, yet do they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed purſue their duty wholly to their own intereſt. Thus and no otherwiſe it is with the profits of Wooll; The State gives ſafety and protection to the peoples works, and the people give wealth and Revenue to the States ſubſiſtence, but each of them to each of them chiefly for their particular benefit. Wooll is the Flower and Strength, the Revenue and Bloud of <hi>England.</hi> It is a Bond uniting the people into Societies and Fraternities for their own Utility. It is the Milk and Honey of the Graſier, and Countrey-man. It is the Gold and Spices of the Weſt and Eaſt <hi>India</hi> to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant and Citizen; In a word, it is the Exchequer of Wealth, and Scepter of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to them all as well at home as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and therefore of full merit to be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37276:10"/>had in perpetual remembrance, defence, and encouragement.</p>
               <p>The Wools of <hi>England</hi> have ever been of great honour and reception abroad, as hath been ſufficiently witneſſed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant amity which for many hundred years hath been inviolably kept between the Kings of <hi>England</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> onely for the benefit of Wool; whoſe ſubjects receiving the Engliſh Wool at ſix pence a pound, returned it (through the manufacture of thoſe induſtrious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) in Cloath at ten ſhillings a yard, to the great enriching of that State, both in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue to their Sovereign, and in imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to their ſubjects; which occaſioned the Merchants of <hi>England</hi> to tranſport their whole Families in no ſmall numbers into <hi>Flanders,</hi> from whence they had a conſtant Trade to moſt parts of the world. And this intercourſe of Trade between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Burgundy,</hi> endured till King <hi>Edward</hi> the third made his mighty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts over <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> when finding fortune more favourable in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37276:11"/>his atchievements then his alledgeate ſubjects were able to maintain, he at once projected how to enrich his people, and to people his new conquered Dominions, and both theſe he deſigned to effect by means of his Engliſh commodity, Wooll; All which he accompliſhed, though not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great difficulties and oppoſitions, for he was not onely to reduce his own ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects home, who were and had long been ſetled in thoſe parts, with their whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; many of which had not ſo certain habitations in <hi>England</hi> as in <hi>Flanders,</hi> but he was alſo to invite Clothiers over to convert his woolls into clothing, (and theſe were the ſubjects of another Prince) or elſe the ſtoppage of the ſtream would ſoon choke the Mill, and then not onely clothing would every where be loſt, but the materials reſting upon his Engliſh Subjects hands, would ſoon ruine the whole Gentry and Yeomanry for want of vending their wools. Now to ſhew how King <hi>Edward</hi> ſmooth'd theſe rough and uneven paſſages, were too tedious to this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37276:11"/>ſhort Narration, though otherwiſe in their contrivance they may be found to be inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, pleaſing, and of great uſe; which relation muſt await another opportunity.</p>
               <p>By this it muſt be granted, that King <hi>Edward</hi> was Wiſe as well as Victorious, &amp; in both he was fortunate, which laſt was much nouriſhed by his bounty; for upon a viſitation made by himſelf to the Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> during his reſidence there, he employed ſuch able Agents amongſt the Flemiſh Clothiers, as (barely upon his promiſes) he prevailed with great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them to come into <hi>England</hi> ſoon after him, where he moſt Royally perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thoſe promiſes, in giving not onely a free Denization to them, but he likewiſe inveſted them with Priviledges and Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities beyond thoſe of his native ſubjects, which peculiarities their poſterities enjoy to this day. Surely the ſeaſonable bounty of a Prince rightly placed, will not be found the weakeſt inſtrument to his atcheive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of honour and ſucceſs. The libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Alexander</hi> amongſt his Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37276:12"/>brought three parts of the world under his Dominion; becauſe amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his valuable conſiderations towards that rich purchaſe, he ſummoned by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation the Creditors of all his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and diſcharged their Debts; wherein af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards divers of the Roman Emperours, as <hi>Julius Caeſar, Pertinax,</hi> and others fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his great example by other bounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions, in which ranke of wiſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Princes, we place this Royal and true Lover of his native Nation, King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for the more ſure eſtabliſhment, and before theſe preparations came into ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, King <hi>Edward</hi> upon his return called a Parliament, and that in the beginning of his Reign, where he ſo wrought with the Commons-Houſe (who had not the leaſt knowledge that the King had moulded the deſign) as after long debate (which all moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in that Houſe ought to undergo) it was preſented to the Lords, and ſo to the King; who amongſt other objections, urged the loſs which muſt neceſſarily befall his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37276:12"/>as well in reſpect of the outward Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy of a Noble upon each ſack of wooll which was to be tranſported, as of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Cuſtome which the cloath paid upon return, according to the rates then eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; but theſe ſoon met with an expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: For the cloath in time to come, muſt needs yield a far greater cuſtome upon that which was to paſs into all parts of the World from <hi>England,</hi> then it could do upon that ſmall return which came onely to the ſervice of <hi>England,</hi> and for the wooll which from that time forward was to be wrought in <hi>England</hi> (with prohibition under penalty of life and limb at the Kings pleaſure, that none in any ſort without the Kings eſpecial licence, ſhould be tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) the Parliament gave unto the King that Subſidy of a Noble upon a ſack, the Collection of which Subſidy the King en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with his Aulnageor: and this was the original, and is the continuance of that money, which at this day is collected and ought to be paid upon all wools wrought into any ſort of manufacture, and is called
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37276:13"/>(though moſt improperly) The Aulnage money, from whence many inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will preſenly appear.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Concerning the Aulnageor, and the legality of his office.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough Aulnage is an office of this Nation, which is of as great anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity as Traffick; for the very Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which comes from <hi>Ulna</hi> in Latine, and <hi>Aulne</hi> in French, either of them ſignifying an Ell, ſhews, that the Aulnageors office was to provide that all ſuch meaſurable commodities as came into <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be of lawful aſſiſe in length and breadth. And from the ancient Records it may be gathered, that in meaſuring the Aulna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geor had the ſame charge upon all forreign meaſurable Merchandizes, from the fineſt Silk, Gold, or Tiſſue, to the courſeſt Hemp, as may be found granted to ſeveral
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37276:13"/>perſons of worth, in the firſt, the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, and the ſeventeenth years of King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond, which was before Clothing was made in <hi>England,</hi> (as hath been ſaid) when that Subſidy upon all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures of wooll was granted to him, and his ſucceſſours, which he entruſted with his Aulnageor, who was nevertheleſs to continue his attendance upon the ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and meaſuring, as anciently he had done. And accordingly he did attend both offices for many years; but finding that the clothing ſo increaſed as it became ſcattered all over the Land, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it was by divers Statutes confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Towns Corporate; inſomuch as the Aulnageor finding the collection of the Subſidy to be of far greater profit, and leſs trouble then the ſallary which related to the ſearching and meaſuring, he neglected thoſe, and betook himſelf wholly to his collection, after which, through the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaviour of Weavers, and other handy-crafts relating to the making, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of Clothing, ſuch and ſo many
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37276:14"/>grew the abuſes to be, as the Cloathiers themſelves became Petitioners to the King to be incorporated into Fraternities, and Societies, and to have officers diſtinct from the Aulnageor to ſearch and meaſure their cloathing; nevertheleſs the Aulnageor continued his office of collecting the ſaid Subſidy, and was enjoyned, upon receipt of his moneys, to affix a ſeal of Lead whereon was to be ſtamped ſome part of the Kings Armes, which is now become a juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that cloath, or elſe that cloath is a great diſhonour to the Nation which bears that ſeale throughout the World; and this ſeal was to be annexed after the meaſurers and ſearchers ſeals were on; to the end that thoſe ſeals denoting what faults thoſe cloaths contained, the cloath was ſeized if it were not vendible, or elſe the faults were diſcovered to the buyer; and for this purpoſe the Aulnageor was to keep a book of his Receipts and Seizures, and once year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to preſent the ſame to the Lord Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, or Barons of the Exchequer, who were to aſſign the Aulnageor his reward;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37276:14"/>and this courſe continued till the Aulnage was made Farmable, which was Enacted by Parliament in the ſeventeenth year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>This relation ſhews that all the officers, Aulnageor, Searcher, and Meaſurer, were to be knowing men, as the Statutes alſo do deliver more at large; for want of which the Trade of cloathing is almoſt quite loſt in <hi>England,</hi> and daily encreaſeth in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by the help of Engliſh wooll, and Fullers earth, the prevention of whoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation is provided by more ancient and ſevere Laws, then any other Laws, then any other Laws relating to Trade; all which is grown originally from the neglect of the Aulnageor, who hath detained the Title from the other officers, and neglected his own, thereby confounding the duties of their works, as though the Aulnageor was then made Collector; yet now the Collector is not (either in propriety of name or execution of office) to be called Aulnageor, yet ſo he accounts himſelf to be to the no ſmall prejudice of cloathing.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37276:15"/>Again, ſince the Aulnageor left his other works of meaſuring and ſearching, his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidy money hath in all times declined, for he wilfully neglecting to ſurvey the cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, taught the Collectors to convey ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from his ſight in point of the Subſidy; inſomuch as they have practiſed to put on counterfeit Seals, or elſe to procure the Seals to be cut from ſuch cloths as have been ſold, and delivered out of the market, of which to this day there is a common trade between the Clothiers and their Chapmans Apprentices, or their Drawers; which deceptions are generally uſed at this day, as ſhall be made more apparent.</p>
               <p>Again, by the Aulnageor's onely neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Clothiers have (through the help of ſome incendiary Attorneys, who would burn their neighbours houſe to roſt their own eggs) found an invention to make a difference between old and new Draperies; a diſtinction not once thought upon in the Primitive Statutes for Clothing, by which they endeavour to work a diviſion in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Aulnage; for the old Drape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37276:15"/>they allow to be paid, but the new, which are Perpetuanoes, Serges, Sayes, and all other Stuffs (though made of wool) they deny to pay, becauſe, ſay they, theſe are not mentioned in the Statute; Now if the anſwer to this ill grounded exception be well weighed, it may appear more agreeable to the Law, that the new Draperies have tranſgreſſed the Statute even in the letter it ſelf, for whoſe benefit they do ſo much quarrel. For the Law ſheweth the preciſe length, breadth, and weight of all Manufactures contained in the Statute; and ſaith, that whatſoever ſhall be made contrary or defective to thoſe ordinations, ſhall be ſeized, without any clauſe or reſervation to the new inventions, which is a chief part of their Plea: nor doth it once name new Draperies, either in point of Aulnage, nor any other conſideration, till about the end of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, and in the beginning of King <hi>James,</hi> where becauſe the exception runs to new Draperies, the Statute ſaith, That payment ſhall be made of the Subſidy or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37276:16"/>Aulnage upon cloath, and all other ſorts of manufactures of Wooll; and one of the moſt learned Judges of his time hath ſet down a poſitive interpretation this doubt (for more it is not) that even in mixtures where the major part is wool, the Aulnage ought to be paid, which concluſion the wiſdome of the laſt age ordained to be kept as authentick in anſwer to this objection. And ſurely the learned Judges have ever been more properly the Interpreters of the arduous points of the Law, then the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torneys, who have no ſuch intereſt as the Judges have in making the Laws, all men holding this for a maxime, that <hi>Ejus eſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem interpretaricujus eſt condere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now concerning this doubt which hath in late years been raiſed about exemption of the new Draperies, and is of as new an invention as the Stuffs in queſtion, it may peradventure prove of little encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or advantage to the oppoſers, if it be conſidered that where a doubt reſts upon the Law, the favour of interpretation doth ever incline to the advantage of the State
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37276:16"/>till a Parliament come, and make a final reſolution, which alſo is ſeldome determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by that grave Aſſembly, to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of their Anceſtors judgments, who in a caſe of ſuch gratitude did not probably intend in any meaſure to abridge their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality to the King.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>An Anſwer to ſuch as call the Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage a Monopoly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are yet another ſort of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers who charge the office of the Aulnage with the ignominious Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of a Monopoly; Surely Monopoly is and hath alwayes been a name of Scandal, for it cannot ſubſiſt without injury to another, and yet there is a glimmering of it in very worthy Societies; For all order, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hath in it a ſort of Majeſty, as is ſeen in Corporations and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, where they exerciſe uncontroulable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37276:17"/>power by vertue of their Statutes; and ſcarcely any of them would bear the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, if their ancient Cuſtomes and Grants ſhould be branded with the Title of Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polizing, yet their whole Societies do ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſavour of a Monopoly, than doth this Subſidy of Aulnage; but we free them both, though of the two the over-ſtrict re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating of a Company carries with it the more reſembling marks of a Monopoly. As for the Aulnage, it may be preſumed that very few of thoſe who terme it a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly, do know what a Monopoly is.</p>
               <p>Monopoly is a Greek word, and intends (in all its interpretations) the diverſion of of a Commerce from its natural courſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of ſome few, by which (for their ſole intereſt) others are prejudiced. This is the opinion of <hi>Althuſius,</hi> and other learned Civilians; whereby it appears that one alone cannot be a Monopolizer, though in ſome carriages of Trade one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone may bear the ignominy of an Ingroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and ſo may raiſe the price of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity which he deals in: yet others ſay,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37276:17"/>that a Monopoly is a kind of Commerce in buying, ſelling, changing or bartering, uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by a few, and ſometimes onely by one perſon to his proper gain, and to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment of other men; But neither in this definition is this Subſidy a Monopoly, for there is neither buying, ſelling, changing, nor bartering in it, but it is a free gift of the Common wealth to that King and his ſucceſſours in this government; Then which no Demiſe or Grant of Land (let the conſideration be what it will) can be more firm in Law, for herein no man is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained or prohibited, nor is any price im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Statute Laws; and theſe two are the onely ſupporters of a Monopoly.</p>
               <p>And whereas from the beginning of this Grant, the want of the Aulnageors ſeal, is the forfeiture of that Cloth which is taken ſo defective, in any Market, Shop, Ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, Cuſtome-houſe, or Ship; Now it is come to a further conſideration, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, for no forreigner will value that cloth which wants this ſeal; becauſe the ſeal (ever containing a part of the Armes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37276:18"/>of <hi>England</hi>) is by forreigners looked upon as a juſtification of the true making of the ſaid cloth, as indeed it ought to be, and herein both a neceſſity of the office, and a neceſſity of the due execution of the office is very apparent, over and beſides a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fity of an exact collection of the States Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, wherein the loſſes are leſs viſible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the practice is continual.</p>
               <p>By that which hath been ſaid the world may ſee that this Subſidy ſtands clear from that charge of a Monopoly, ſeeing it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offends in equity, by ſupplanting or undermining anothers freedom of equal rank and condition, nor in utility, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a particular price to the common inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for the Aulnageors private benefit; without the proof of which particulars, a Monopoly cannot ſubſiſt. And we have this moreover to ſay, That neither the Grand Aſſembly of Parliament, nor the leſſer Brotherhoods of Companies, would conclude it to be worthy or juſt that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conventions ſhall brand their Acts with ſo ignominious a title as that of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37276:18"/>which being granted, this Subſidy is out of danger, for it hath the conſent and fortification of more Acts of Parliament, by hundreds, then any temporal affair whatſoever.</p>
               <p>And yet you may be pleaſed further to take an additional preſident, both where and why the King hath of his own good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs forborne his Aulnage or Subſidy; In ſome of the North parts of this Nation, whileſt clothing hath been in the infancy, and where the ſubſtance was very courſe, as as it were but for practice to future in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe; the King upon petition of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, hath (for their better encouragement) been pleaſed for a time to remit his Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, even upon ſuch as they call old Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, they allowing it to be chargeable with the ſaid Subſidy; but ſo as ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures have afterwards fallen into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant payment, and do continue the ſame unto this day without any exception or once pleading the ſaid favour of the King now to excuſe them.</p>
               <p>Take yet if you pleaſe a preſident of a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37276:19"/>forreign nature to this work. There is in <hi>Dorſet</hi> ſhire, in that part which was the Forreſt of <hi>Blackmore,</hi> an Impoſition upon all the Tenants, called <hi>White Hart Money,</hi> of as long a ſtanding peradventure as this of the Aulnageors Subſidy, though not of ſo worthy a foundation, where the Land and Inhabitants upon it by way of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for killing the Kings <hi>White Hart,</hi> have for divers hundreds of years, paid, and do (notwithſtanding the diſafforeſting the ſame) ſtill continue conſtantly to pay a yearly Tax, which the State doth upon no condition remit or forbear to demand and receive. And ſurely no man that is a Tenant there will endanger his Leaſe for want of paying this Tax, yet it never was renewed, if ever it was eſtabliſhed, by Parliament, or had it been ſo grounded, it could never have been called otherwiſe then a puniſhment; and let all men judge if a puniſhment have as good right to charge the people, as hath an act of their own grateful bounty.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:37276:19"/>
               <p> But this particular of the equity of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the new Draperies is come to ſuch a height of oppoſition, as peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it may not become this humble relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and, as it were, ſingle opinion, to wade too far in ſo troubled waters. Therefore becauſe the Aulnageors deputies are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes men of that integrity in their places as is required, we will now proceed to ſhew you wherein their illegal carriages are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and the execution of their office may be reformed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Shewing the illegal execution of the Aulnageors office.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe legality of the Aulnage or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy is (by that which hath been ſaid) viſible to all who will not be blind, but the illegality in the execution is carried with a far greater ſecrecy; When the Aulnageor (whoſe ancient duty enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37276:20"/>him to ſearch and meaſure all Trade which came into <hi>England</hi>) was by King <hi>Edward,</hi> as hath been ſaid, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to receive that Subſidy which the Parliament had granted unto him upon all ſuch Woolls as in time to come ſhould be wrought into any kind of manufacture in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> he was alſo ſtill en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged as formerly, to viſit, ſearch, and meaſure all ſuch cloths as were to be made in <hi>England;</hi> but finding that the diſperſing of the Manufactures was of much more difficulty, pains and charge to him in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the ſeveral Countreys, and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Towns wherein clothing was placed, then it was when the clothing which was made in forreign parts, came onely to the Cuſtome houſes, where by caſting a line of ſeven yards in length, four times over the cloth, his meaſuring office was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but now the clothing was become ſcattered all over the Land. He conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with himſelf that his Collectorſhip was of more gains, and far leſs pains then his former office of Aulnage, which conſiſted
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37276:20"/>of ſearching for the truth in making, and of meaſuring for the aſſize of lengths and breadths; and that of theſe two works there were many branches both of charge and trouble, and that the Reward by Law eſtabliſhed, was very ſmall; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented himſelf with the execution of that which had moſt eaſe, and moſt profit, whereupon clothing ſpeedily corrupted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many abuſes, as being in a manner leſt without Survey, each man doing what pleaſed or profited himſelf without any reverence to the Law, or fear of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>The Clothiers therefore coming to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to their general Market, and there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring their grievances, and complaining each to other of their abuſive ſervants, falſe Weavers, and the like; they applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the State for remedies, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came incorporated into Societies and Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternities, and to have the works which were made in and about them brought into their Hals, &amp; there to be ſearched, meaſured, and ſealed; which order doth in ſome kind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37276:21"/>to this day, and this alſo pleaſed the Aulnageor, who by a Deputy with ſeals placed in ſuch a Town diſpatched his work with eaſe. In which times alſo the Aulna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geor having the cuſtody and uſe of the Kings money, was anſwerable for the ſame to the State but once every year, and then paſſed his Accounts with great favour from the Lord Treaſurer, to whom he alſo at the ſame time preſented a book, containing the relation of the moneys he had in that year received for the Subſidy, and of the ſeizures he had made upon the defective clothes; which being done he had his <hi>quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and his reward for the year paſt, which he received ſometimes by the appointment of the Lord Treaſurer, and ſometimes from the Barons of the Exchequer; for from one or ſome of them he likewiſe received his commiſſion to ſeize into his hands all ſuch cloths as were not ſtatutable in aſſiſe, and ſubſtance, as alſo ſuch as were put to ſale without the Subſidy ſeal.</p>
               <p>It was no longer ſince then in King <hi>James</hi> his Reign, that the Mayor of one of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37276:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>the moſt eminent Cities in <hi>England</hi> for clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, was compelled by the Aulnage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, <hi>nolens volens,</hi> to ſeize his own cloths (which were taken in offence) to the Kings uſe; which Mayor afterwards compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Aulnageor for no leſs then an hundred pounds. The ſame power alſo hath the Aulnageor over cloths which are not of aſſiſe, though in the preſence of any Mayor, Bayliff, or other Magiſtrate, which argues that there is great credit and truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon the Aulnageor. Beſides, the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute doth allow him an half penny upon a cloth for his pains in affixing his ſaid ſeal, which half penny in thoſe times was in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue worth two pence in theſe days, &amp; yet his pains were not then ſo much by a tenth part as now they are, as alſo the faults were few and eaſily ſuppreſt. But the abuſes herein ſoon increaſed to ſuch height, as they begot him great trouble; and therefore he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected meaſuring and ſearching offices, but ſtill kept the name of Aulnageor, under which Title he doth to this day execute the office of Collecting the Subſidy, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that the Aulnage, when indeed the true
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37276:22"/>Aulnage is the meaſuring onely, and of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity eſtabliſhed by Laws far more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent then any Parliament in <hi>England;</hi> of which we ſhall ſpeedily ſay more when we ſpeak of meaſuring.</p>
               <p>The Aulnageor is by the Statute required to be a perſon qualified to the place with knowledge and a reſponſible eſtate, as alſo for the execution of the place, he is to be an Engliſh-man; but for receiving the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and revenue, there hath ever been ſome perſon of honour and principal dignity thereto deputed; which office ſome Queens and Princes have not been aſhamed to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo. And further it is obſervable, to the credit of the Aulnageor, that in all Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, where Statutes were ordained in order to Clothing, the Aulnageors pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and priviledges were ever preſerved; which gracious providence ought much to work upon his care, as it is evidently a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature to all men of his honour.</p>
               <p>In the ſeventeenth year of the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, the Aulnage was made Farmable, and then the Aulnageors
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37276:22"/>Fee was eſtabliſhed; ſoon after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were farmed out, ſome to one, ſome to another, as pleaſed the King reigning. In the beginning of King <hi>James</hi> his reign, this office was by him Farmed to <hi>Lodowick,</hi> late Duke of <hi>Richmond</hi> and <hi>Lennox,</hi> for the term of about ſixty years (whereof many were expired) with the revertion of a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Rent; the reverſion of which Leaſe, after the Duke <hi>Lodowick</hi> his deceaſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended upon his moſt Honourable Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Eſme</hi> Duke of <hi>Lennox;</hi> who diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the profits thereof to his younger chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the poſſeſſion of the whole is now in right deſcended upon the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Lord <hi>D'Aubigny,</hi> as onely Survi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor and Heir to his Father and Uncles; who being in minority of age, the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the place is by his Honourable Guardians diſpoſed to ſuch perſons as to them ſeems meet; who again for their beſt improvement of its profits, do grant Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Deputations to others, with a clauſe and penalty of re-entry upon non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment of their Rents; by which means
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37276:23"/>many controverſies do grow, for amongſt the diverſity of Tenants, ſuch ſuits and troubles do ariſe, as in the interim the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers not knowing whom to obey, do paſs without any ſeal, or paying any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy, to the great detriment of the State and the Honourable Aulnageor, whoſe rights failing, his rents alſo to the State muſt neceſſarily ſo do.</p>
               <p>All this while the cloth wants the juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the ſeal, to the great confuſion of the Clothiers, for a double ſeal may not be put upon their cloths, upon penalty of five pounds for every ſuch ſeal twice annexed, and without a Seal the cloth will have no credit in ſale, beſides that it is liable to be ſeized by the ſeveral Aulnageors; for which cauſes the Clothier is encouraged, and in ſome ſort compelled to offend (which needs not) for rather then the Clothier will have his cloth diſhonoured for want of the ſeal, he will either counterfeit a ſeal, or elſe covenant with the Drapers ſervants or Drawers to cut the ſeals from ſuch cloths as have paſſed the Marker, whereas the Draper is by the Law required to keep his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37276:23"/>ſeal upon his cloth to the laſt remnant, and then to demoliſh the ſeal, and by theſe opportunities the Clothier juſtifies all his faults to the buyer.</p>
               <p>Again, the preſent execution of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is by Deputies, who for ſaving charge do deliver upon account their ſeales, either to the Clothiers themſelves, or to the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to put them to the cloth after ſcowring, or elſe they are intruſted in ſome ſervants hand of mean quality and leſs knowledge, with whom the Clothiers for eaſie rewards can prevail to paſs ſuch jugling tricks as may better be diſcerned in the Countrey, (for one half that are made come not into the Market to be ſold) and then they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex counterfeits, or having the ſeals in their own power, they hang them ſo ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the cloth as they can, without any defacing, take them off again after the cloth hath paſſed the Market, and affix them to others; by theſe proceedings all the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers faults are concealed, and ſo they paſs to that part of the world where that cloth goes, which brands the clothing of this Nation, and advanceth that of other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37276:24"/>Countreys. This was lately ſeen in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where ſome Engliſh cloths, faulty enough, were preſented in open Markets, and a diſgraceful Proclamation being pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, the cloths were therewithal given to the view of the people to be warranted by the Armes of <hi>England,</hi> whereby not onely great ſcandal was drawn upon Engliſh clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and Merchants, but their own was brought into better credit, which not long before that were by thouſands baniſhed out of <hi>France</hi> for Rags, and Cheats.</p>
               <p>There is yet another great prejudice which comes to the Aulnageors loſs, by ſuch manner of entruſting ſeals with ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Clothiers, or Clothiers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to affix them; for whereas the cloths are regulated by the Statute both in their length, breadth, and weight, yet they will moſt cunningly draw three clothes into one, and then cut it into two clothes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the State is defrauded of a third part of the Subſidy; and this they do uſually and ſo neatly, as a very good Drawer (not knowing it) ſhall not eaſily diſcern the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37276:24"/>fraud. This covenanting for ſeals doth alſo diſcover a falſe intention in the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier, even in the very bargaining; for whereas a cloth, by the primitive ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ought to weigh ſixty four pounds, the Subſidy payment whereof amounts but to a groat, yet the Clothier uſually payes ſix pence a piece for his ſeals, under colour that he would not have his clothes opened, or any way diſordered before they go into the Market; yet the very truth is, he would not have his faults or defects diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; and then again he ſecures the doubts of weighing, which would give the Aulnageor as good information, but would much reveal the Clothiers diſhoneſty, by the deficiency which would be found in want of weight; which ſhall be further declared, when we come to ſpeak of the Searchers office, to which it hath now chief relation: In the interim we will proceed to ſhew what prejudice is befallen to clothing by want of the Aulnageors duty in meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:37276:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Office of meaſuring, anclently called the Aulnageor.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MEaſuring is a work of that extent in government, as without it no man knows his own, nor is there any ſuch thing as a mans own without Menſuration; how divine it is let <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeak, who ſaith, <hi>That divers weights and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers meaſures are abomination to God;</hi> we have now to do with meaſuring, that of weighing more properly coming within the diſcourſe of Searching, whereof we ſhall preſently ſpeak.</p>
               <p>We cannot properly wade into the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of meaſuring, unleſs we begin our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry from the originals of clothing, which reſts upon ſuch as mingle, card, and ſpin Woolls. The minglers are uſually in great fault, for whereas by the Statute, clothing is to be made of Fleece wooll onely, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs they mingle Fell woolls and Lambs
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:37276:25"/>Wools with Fleece-wools, which are of natures contrary one to another, and as contrary to the <hi>Statute Lawes</hi> one to be mingled with another; yet theſe are daily practiſed: From whence come theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, that the Cloth which is made of ſuch diſproportioned Stuffe, doth ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it uneven cockly, purſey, and rewey; and howſoever the Art of the <hi>Cloth worker</hi> doth in ſome meaſure cover theſe faults, yet that Cloth containes Deceptions and abuſes, which will eaſily be found in wearing.</p>
               <p>Again, there is a great abuſe in mingling fine Flox with long Wools (though courſe) theſe being Carded together, do (with no little care) hold Spinning and Working, but do prove moſt deceitfull and abuſive in uſe and wearing. The uſe of ſhort Thrums produceth the ſame Couzenage in working, and abuſe in wearing: For when they have cut the thrums into ſhort lengths as they mean to uſe them, then they lay them to ſteep in ſtrong Lye or Liquor, which openeth the Threads into Wooll, which makes the Yarne more uneven then
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37276:26"/>the Flocks; the practice of this is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and intollerable, inſomuch as it hath been and is publiquely known, that Cloths have been made of two parts Flocks and Thrums, and but one part Wooll; and that which helps the deception is, that it carries good and faire ſatisfaction to the Eye, but in wearing and ſervice will not laſt a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that time which a ſound Cloth made of perfect Wooll will do: But here the Clothier alledgeth the loſſe that will be to him of his Flocks and Thrums, which is as readily anſwered; for there are ſeverall ſorts of commodities to which they are only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and where the uſe of them may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred; the thing we complain of is, when they are uſed to evil purpoſe, with intent to make unlawfull gain, and uſed with ſuch ſubtilty and cunning, as the Buyers igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance may be abuſed.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Weaver</hi> is proverbially a Theefe, to which he is the more encouraged, by being acquainted with the Clothiers practiſes in falſe mingling his Yarne; and therefore in ſleying his Warp, he will uſually ſteal a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37276:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>whole Sley, which coſiſts of above thirty threads, and with inſtruments which he hath prepared, he will hold out his Cloth to the full breadth which the Statute requires; and though this cloth will ſufficiently ſhew the Robberies of the Weaver when it comes to the Mill, yet ſo ſoon as it is ſcow<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed, and comes to the Cloth-worker, he with his Tenters will bring it to the in<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ended breadth; Such a Cloth will to a man of judgment ſoon be diſcovered, for it will feel ſlender, looſe, and hollow in hand: Herein reſts the Weavers chiefe gaines, and becauſe theſe deceptions cannot be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without the Clothiers knowledge, he endeavours to make him amends by fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cozening the Chapman, for he cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly knits together the long Thrums left of Broad Cloths, which cannot be wrought to the ſhortneſſe of narrow Clothes, and mingling them with Yarne of better na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where by the help which each gives to other, the workmanſhip is eafed, but the wearing is highly abuſed; For by the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences of the many knots in ſuch a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37276:27"/>Cloth, which after ſcowring are Burled out, and then ſhut up again in the Mill, when this Cloth comes to wearing, it will ſoon prove to be full of holes, and will not be laſting.</p>
               <p>And yet further the Weaver is artificiall in his cheats, for in ſleying his Warps he wil caſt the Yarn to prove fine about a foot breadth from the Liſts, which is ſo farre commonly as the Chapman looks into the Cloth, or the making it up with pleights and threads will permit, when the reſt of the Cloth is warpt quite through with a for courſer Yarne: It is alſo a common practice for the Weaver to cover a courſe Warp, being ſpunne hard and ſmall, with a fine Wooffe, ſpunne ſoft and round; this conceales the Warpe from ſight, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in working would appeare; but in wearing it is ſufficiently found, and the practice of this is ordinary upon ſuch Cloths as are ſold rough.</p>
               <p>They have yet another deceptious help for their maſters, which is to ſhoot in a fine Wooſe at each end of the Cloth, which
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37276:27"/>ſerveth for a muſter to ſhew and ſell the Cloth, but all the reſt of the Cloth is farre worſe; and theſe ends doubtleſly want not workmanſhip to drive them in the Loome, for better ſhew in ſale.</p>
               <p>Such as make ſtuffs called new Draperies, that is to ſay, Serges, Seyes, Perpetuanoes, and the like, do deſpiſe all Forme and order enjoyned by the <hi>Lawes</hi> to ſuch kind of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures in their making, and therefore the wonder is leſſe why they ſo earneſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, and by litigious and tedious Suites at Law do oppoſe the view of ſuch <hi>Draperies</hi> to the <hi>Aulnager:</hi> For to give you an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance upon that of <hi>Perpetuanoes</hi> (which was a Clothing of this Nation of princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall eſteem both at home and abroad) theſe ſtuffs in their firſt ordination had their pitch in the Loome at twelve hundred, which gave them ſubſtance and eſtimation, and being of acceptable weare to the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> are now brought to eight hundred in their pitch, and yet made to hold out their length and breadth; and ſome Merchants (who are a ſcandall to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37276:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch as reſpect their reputation and Credit) do uſually buy ſlight <hi>Seyes,</hi> which by arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and cunning in Milling are brought to be <hi>Baſtard Perpetuanoes,</hi> and in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure acceptable to the ſight, but ſo unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table are they in ſervice and wearing, as they do diſcredit that Commodity, which for many yeares hath held as quick and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditable a Trade in their kind, as any Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of Wool have done, which in theſe times is almoſt quite loſt.</p>
               <p>Now for <hi>Kerſeys,</hi> it is to be noted, that the original of that kind of clothing had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten good reputation for its durable wearing both at home &amp; abroad, but of late years a ſort of cloth calld <hi>Mancheſter</hi> or <hi>Lancaſhire Plaines,</hi> which were uſually made for <hi>Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> and no other, about a yard in breadth, are now become the greedy purchaſe of ſome Merchants, who cut them in lengths according to that of a <hi>Kerſey,</hi> which being dreſſed and dyed in the forme of a <hi>Kerſey,</hi> are both at home and abroad vented for <hi>Kerſeys,</hi> which Cloth in wearing doth very much diſgrace that which is true of that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37276:28"/>kind, and doth not a little abuſe the wearer.</p>
               <p>And the more to abuſe this ſort of Cloth, which for long time hath given great cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> there be Merchants who deceptiouſly to imitate thoſe <hi>Devonſhire Kerſeys,</hi> do cauſe counterfeits to be made in <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> out of <hi>Waſhers</hi> and <hi>halfe Thicks</hi> which have contained ſuch length and breadth, with ſlop Liſts as true <hi>Devonſhire Kerſeys</hi> are uſed to do: Theſe when they have been dreſſed, dyed, and hot preſſed, have poſſed the Seas for <hi>Devonſhire Kerſeys,</hi> to the great abuſe and diſcredit of that ſort of Cloth; whereas the true <hi>Devonſhire Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeys</hi> ought to be marked at the head end, but being defective they are to be jagged at both ends, or to have the head Forell to be cut off, and the offender to be Fined as he deſerves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:37276:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Meaſuring.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT was requiſite that theſe particulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of abuſes ſhould firſt be related, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is neceſſary the Meaſurer ſhould be a man known in them, and many more deceptions which are incident and dayly practiſed upon Clothing: The Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer is now become a diſtinct Officer about Clothing, who was once the chiefe of that Employment, known by the name of <hi>Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageor,</hi> the branches of whoſe Office, were Searching, Meaſuring, and collecting the Subſidy, formerly related; and a greater injury could not have come to the intereſt of the <hi>Common good,</hi> then the improvident ſeparation of the Name &amp; office of <hi>Aulna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geor,</hi> who now only beareth the title, but to his own and the Nations general loſſe, hath formerly neglected and now is diſmiſſed of that beneficiall worke, wherein almoſt eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular mans good is intereſſed.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:37276:29"/>
               <p> And the <hi>Aulnageor</hi> is herein as blameable towards himſelfe, for though through his negligence, the Offices of meaſuring and ſearching became the employment of other men, who were to be ſworn in Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the Mayor or Bayliff, yet was the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch men to be preſented to the ſaid Magiſtrate by the <hi>Aulnageor;</hi> from the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of which theſe miſchiefs are growne: Firſt, that ignorant perſons, as <hi>Taylors, Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Glovers, Butchers, Smiths,</hi> and the like, who have no judgment at all in Cloth, are choſen into the offices of meaſuring and ſearching: or, Secondly, if there be men elected of ſome knowledge in clothing, yet ſuch men are choſen by the Magiſtrate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who in all clothing Townes is ever a Clothier; now if Malefactours may make choice of their own Iudges and Iury, it is apparent how the Common-wealth would be eaſed of Crimes and Malefactors: and it is no better here, for the men by this office being to be regulated or puniſhed are the Magiſtrates themſelves, as is before ſaid, &amp; therefore not probably to be queſtioned by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37276:30"/>their own Subſtitutes: Thirdly, theſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ought annually to be changed, but now and of long time they are continued for life, or for many yeares, as they can prevaile with the Mayors in ſucceſſion; which ſeldome failes, becauſe each man in his courſe hath need of them: and how foule and prejudiciall a crime this doth prove both to the State and People, ſhall preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be found in our Diſcourſe upon Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>We have formerly ſhewed that all Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in <hi>England</hi> was confined to Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and great Townes, where in their Halls it was to undergo meaſuring and ſearching, and ſo it doth in ſuch an imperfect and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial way, as hath been declared: But in the Villages which are not Incorporated, and where there is no magiſtrate, there is alſo no Officer in theſe Super-intendencies of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring and ſearching, by which meanes all their Clothes which paſſe immediately to the Ports, and thence to Forreign parts, are neither meaſured nor ſearched, whereby it may appear what vaſt Summes of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidy
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37276:30"/>money are loſt, (for ſuch Clothes ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or never come under the <hi>Aulnageors</hi> hand) or if they be ſealed, it is performed (as hath been ſaid) by deceptious and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Seales, and though true ones be ſometimes taken from the <hi>Aulnageors</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, yet are they kept for the more viſible uſe, and counterfeits clapt on.</p>
               <p>For ſuch as are not meaſured in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try (as out of Corporations none are) they coming to the generall Markets in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> are there by power of the Lord Mayor meaſured by the City ſworn Meaſurer, as he is called; and here the Clothier is in ſome ſort puniſhed for his other diſhoneſties but not legally; for when they are brought into the ſworn Meaſurers hands, he there keeps them for ſome time, under pretence of leiſure, which by others clothes is prevented, during which time the Clothes are ſo handled amongſt thoſe Officers, as their owners dayly complain of abuſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable: For though the Clothiers which are makers of them, do meaſure them at home, yet after they come out of the ſworn
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37276:31"/>Meaſurers hand, they receive them ſhorter by foure or ſix yards, after their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, then they delivered them; and it hath been &amp; peradventure yet is a practice of ſuch as have them ſo long under their cuſtody, to cut a yard, foure or five out of the midle or beſt part of a Cloth, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to have it ſo curiouſly drawn up again as the place cannot be found: So again out of fine white or ſingle coloured Cloths, they have cut what quantities they pleaſe, and with the like neatnes have drawn in as much of a courſer Cloth of the ſame co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, whilſt the abuſed Clothier for want of witneſſe knowes not certainly whom to accuſe, himſelf having before he came from home meaſured his cloth before good wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and therefore muſt reſt contented with the Loſſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe abuſes amongſt the ſworn Officers do teach the Clothiers to practice dayly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, ſome of which they do own and countenance; for they have in theſe late yeares invented the making of Stuffs of fantaſticall faſhions, to which they give
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37276:31"/>ſuch names as the Law doth not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend; theſe under the name of new inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do defraud the Law in their making, the State in their Revenue, and the People in their wearing: For to the Law they are not known either by name or aſſize of length and breadth; to the State they dare not appeare, unleſſe by quarrels, contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Suites; and to the wearer they are ſo welcome, as where he once buyes them he will come no more for the moſt part: Anciently the cloth Ray, and coloured clothes were limited to their length and breadth; ſince which time proviſion was made by ſeveral Lawes for Broad Clothes, Kerſeys, Dozens, Penniſtones, Cottons, and the like, which did appoint unto them a length, breadth, &amp; weight; but now if theſe preſent Manufactures be held before the Law, as once was <hi>Ioſephs Coate</hi> to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſurely the Statutes beholding ſuch raggs as are now made in compariſon of the ancient glorious clothing, without doubt the Law will take up <hi>Iacobs</hi> wonder and indignation, that ſome wicked beaſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37276:32"/>hath ſlaine the Ordinance, and torne the Coate; nevertheleſſe <hi>Iacobs</hi> Law, that is, <hi>Anno quarto Iacobi,</hi> if it be ſeriouſly perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and put in execution, will give a ſpeedy remedy to theſe inſufferable abuſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of the Searcher and his Office.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Officers of Meaſurer and Searcher may better be called the <hi>Gemini,</hi> then Twinnes, for they are ſo much entrayned one within another, as in ſome paſſages we cannot ſpeak of one without the other; for though the Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers office be of firſt uſe in clothing, yet is the Meaſurer to ſee the Cloths meaſured when they are wet at the Mill, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward when they are ſcowred and dreſſed, and this courſe the Law provides, to the end the wickedneſſe of the Weaver may be prevented, if it be poſſible; for between the wetting and working of the cloth, there
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37276:32"/>ought to be but halfe a quarter ſtrained in breadth, and one yard in length, whereas it is now become a great courteſie to the cloth if they ſtreine it but a quarter and half in breadth, and five yards in length, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in theſe dayes go beyond this heighth.</p>
               <p>We have a Proverb which ſaith, <hi>where God hath his Church, the Devill will have his Chappell;</hi> ſo, ſoon after clothing came into <hi>England,</hi> deceptions and abuſes were pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed about it: For inſtance, there was in the thirty and ninth yeare of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> a Law made concerning the abuſes in clothing, wherein orders were provided that all ſorts of clothes ſhould be truly ſearched, and their juſt contents of length and weight ſet upon every Piece, the Seale reciting the word (Searched) upon it, and this to be done upon pain of forfeiture; This Law doubtleſly intended the generall good and reformation, yet in regard there was but two Counties named, which had moſt offended in this matter, therefore would all offenders in other places confine that Law to thoſe two Counties, wherefore
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37276:33"/>in the three &amp; fourtieth year of that Queens Reign, the Parliament did interpret that Act to extend over all and ſingular of woollen Broad-clothes, half-clothes, Ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Cottons, Dozens, Peniſtons, Frizes, Ruggs, and all other woollen clothes of what nature, kind, or name ſoever they be, or ſhall be made within this Realm, to be viewed, ſearched, ſealed, and ſubjected to penalties in ſuch manner and forme, to ſuch purpoſe and intents reſpectively, as was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to thoſe Clothes: There is no doubt but if the queſtion now ſtarted between old and new Draperies had then been thought upon, the Subſidy of Aulnage would then as preciſely have been cleared, if in thoſe words (ſubjected to all penalties) it be not already contained.</p>
               <p>But to come more exactly to the neceſſity of the Searcher, (of which officers in Townes and Villages not Corporate there is none) we will here enter upon the deceipts as they are dayly found, and as the Law detects them. The firſt deceipt uſed about Woolls, (whoſe owne innocence is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:37276:33"/>as much as the Sheeps which beares it) is commonly by mingling it in divers kinds, that is to ſay, <hi>Fleece woolls, Fell woolls,</hi> and <hi>Lambs woolls,</hi> which are contrary of nature to be wrought together; this compoſition we have formerly denoted to render a cloth uneven, cockly, purſey, and the like; that mingling fine flocks with long Wools, but courſe, doth give an uneven thread in ſpinning, and proves deceitfull in wearing; that ſhort Thrums opened into wooll, and carded again with other wooll, which is worſe then that of Flocks, doth alſo much embaſe the thread, and yet it is common to put two parts of Flocks and Thrums into a Cloth, and but one of good wooll, which though it coſeneth the eye, yet doth it prove ſo weake in wearing, as it will not laſt a fourth part of that time which a perfect cloth will do.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſome others are before recited, therefore we will proceed to the Mill, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when a cloth comes, it would be there truly ſearched even by the Mill it ſelf, which would lay open the faults; but the Millers
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37276:34"/>art prevents it, for with tallow, pigs dung, and urine, they keep in the flocks and helpe the thicking; and when a cloth proves ſlender, and will not thick kindly in the Mill, by reaſon of the defects, then they helpe it with the medicine of oate-meale, and the like, which remaining in the cloth, makes it feell faſt and thick in hand untill it come to dreſſing, where all that ſtopping vaniſheth, but there the Clothworker uſeth his art to preſerve it from ſhame: When a cloth wanteth of his ſubſtance &amp; allowance in yarn, as hath formerly been obſerved, the defects would ſoon be diſcovered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clean ſcowred, thicked and dryed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſuch a caſe it ſhall be ſcowred by halfes, the oyle and ſeame being left in it, in which filth they will thick it up, which proves noyſome in wearing.</p>
               <p>Then come we to the Tenters, which with great penalties are forbidden upon rough cloths, yet in the Counties where thoſe cloths are made, and ought to be ſold rough, there are Tenters erected as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly as in other places; and whereas
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37276:34"/>ſuch cloths ought to be left in the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as they come from the Mill, they are nevertheleſſe brought upon the Tenters, the better to conceale the recited abuſes in the yarn, and weaving, which the Mill leaves ſhamefull in cockles, purſineſſe, and narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in ſome places then other; theſe faults they pretend to even out, under which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour they ſtraine them beyond the limits al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for dreſſed cloths.</p>
               <p>Again, becauſe the Clothe; thus ſtrained do leave viſible marks upon the Liſts and ends, whereby the abuſes offered unto them may be plainly manifeſted, there the Cloth-worker goes to worke, who with a wet cloth and a hot Iron runnes over the ſides and ends, and ſo ſmoothly ſhuts up the tongues of the Tenters as they tell no tales. And when by the ſame tentering the cloth doth prove hollow in hand, then is the ſame wet cloth and hot Iron uſed again about a ſpan deep from the liſts, (the binding up of the cloth with threads keeping it from fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examination) and for ſo much the cloth feels cloſe in hand, but the buyer muſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37276:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>take the reſt as he finds it: when any of their clothes fall out much too light, then they hang them abroad in an evening, and ſometimes all night to receive the dew, and rather then faile, they ſpout water upon the cloth to weighten it, which will give it no leſſe then ſeven or eight pounds in additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall heavineſſe, beſides that it makes it feele more kindly in hand; and this is ſo cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done, as it ſhall very hardly be perceived; nevertheleſſe many of them are ſo over-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as in their travailes into far parts, whil'ſt they lye long in the hot holds of the Ships, they become rotten and are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe tricks, the Cloth-workers have a profeſſed Art or Myſterie of their Trade in dreſſing clothes: For inſtance, the weavers falſhood in making up clothes with flocks and thrums would be to litle pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if the Cloth-worker did not joyne his deceipts; for finding thoſe clothes to prove too tender for honeſt workmanſhip, there he will rowe them dry, and worke them with ſolace, and ſoft liquor, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37276:35"/>the flocks from the force of the Teſſel, and yet they will make it riſe with a ground to worke upon in ſhearing: and in ſtreining upon the Tenters (as hath been ſaid) they will ſo ſtretch a cloth, as they will bring that to thirty yards, which being wet again, a third part of the length and breadth is quite vaniſhed.</p>
               <p>A Kerſey is allowed to be ſtreined but one naile in breadth, and halfe a yard and no more in length, yet ſuch a <hi>Devonſhire</hi> kerſey of onely twelve yards long, hath been ſtreined a quarter of a yard in breadth, and three yards in length; ſo as in breadth and length the Tenters have lent ſuch a cloth one halfe of the piece, which is no ſooner come to the water, but the moiety flyes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibly away, worſe then <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> tricks. Again, if a cloth by much milling do runne in, ſo as it cauſeth more then ordinary la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to bring it to the length and breadth which they appoint for it, then they will uſe warme water in the Tentering thereof, but more after the warmth of the Sunne, which they know will make a cloth yield
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:37276:36"/>any way in ſtretching.</p>
               <p>Finally in the finiſhing their worke of rowing and ſhearing, they will uſe a deceit with flocks of the ſame colour of the cloth, which they can ſheare as ſmall as duſt, this they mingle with ſolace, &amp; ſpread upon the muſters, and where the cloth may be ſeen, which makes it to ſeem much finer then it is, and feele more ſubſtantiall in hand; But if this cloth lye a while after dreſſing, the ſolace dryeth up, and thoſe flocks fly away, leaving the cloth in his own nature again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of deceits in colours and dying.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DYing is of great importance, and of double concernment towards clothing; one in behalfe of the people which uſe it, the other towards the woolls, cloths, and ſtuffs which are dyed: on the peoples part it is ſo beneficiall, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers weighty Statutes made for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37276:36"/>of it, do relate the livelyhood which it doth give to many thouſands of people; and therefore the Lawes ordained for it, do under great penalties oblige the profeſſors of dying in wools, that they ſhall not teach their myſtery to a forreign nation; yet in late yeares there have ſeverall Engliſh-men tranſported themſelves into <hi>Holland</hi> for no other cauſe, but to inrich themſelves with the ſpoyles of their own Country; and have there practiſed, communicated, and taught the myſteries of dying colours in wooll, ſo that the reformation hereof may ſeem to be too late undertaken; yet breention of the like falſe bretheren in time to come may be provided, partly by encouraging the Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at home, which cannot better be done then by care that one do not undermine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother by faleneſs in dying: And again, by keeping the materials (which are eſpecially wools and white cloths) from being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported (as the Statutes do enjoyne) that is to ſay, without Licenſe from the State, where alſo the petition ought well to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37276:37"/>
               <p> The other part of importance in dying, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the woolls, cloths, and ſtuffs, and therein that the colours be true and well grounded, for the truth of the colour is as materiall as the goodneſs of the cloth, becauſe oftentimes a good cloth is ſpoyled by a bad colour, and as oftentimes doth a good colour mend and preferre a meane cloth: Such as intend to give beauty to falſe colours (as colours do to evil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions) do practice with that ſo much prohibited ingredient called <hi>Logwood,</hi> which though forbidden by the Statute under ſevere penalties, is nevertheleſſe as commonly uſed as colours; yet it is known to be a cheat as bad as picking a pocket, for it barely gives a vading gloſſe to the thing dyed, which changeth with the Sun, or Fire, blowes away with the wind, and alters with the aire; in a word, this abuſe is intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, though common, and gives great diſcredit to the commodity ſo dyed.</p>
               <p>The ground of good and durable colours is ſubſtantiall <hi>Woading,</hi> without which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers colours cannot perfectly be made, that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:37276:37"/>is to ſay, Blacks, Ruſſets, Tawneys, Purples, Greenes, and the like; many of theſe colours in late yeares are made without the juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able foundation of <hi>woading,</hi> which though they appeare beautifull to the eye by the helpe of <hi>Logwood,</hi> as hath been ſaid; yet in uſe and wearing they prove very falſe and diſgracefull: to ſome colours they give a flight ground of <hi>Woad,</hi> though farre too weake to the depth of the colour it beares; nevertheleſs they have the art to ſet up a a true <hi>woad-marke,</hi> or <hi>woad-roſe</hi> upon the piece, at a far richer depth then the cloth is <hi>woaded</hi> throughout: and ſome have yet a more neat and ſubtill art to ſet a <hi>woad-mark</hi> upon a cloth with a little <hi>Indico,</hi> when there is no ſort of <hi>woad</hi> at all upon the cloth; ſuch as will do juſtly, muſt ſet a <hi>woaded ſeale</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>woaded colours,</hi> which is better and more juſtifiable then the <hi>Roſe marke</hi> ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed.</p>
               <p>There be five eſpecial degrees in <hi>woading,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>a Huling, a Plounket. a Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, an Azure,</hi> and <hi>a Blew:</hi> every one of theſe exceedeth another in value, yet is every one
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:37276:38"/>of them fit for ſome colours: it is therefore very requiſite that each of theſe degrees be truly expreſſed upon the <hi>woad-ſeale,</hi> that the buyer may know the truth of that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour which he hath for his money; by which reformation thoſe intolerable abuſes would be prevented, which cauſe ſuch numbers of cloths and ſtuffs to paſſe beyond the Seas, and there to be dreſſed and dyed, to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great prejudice and detriment of the good people of this Nation, who might live, and very plentifully increaſe, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining themſelves as happily, as any other people upon thoſe imployments.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Aulnageor</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath alſo the intuition of colours, in a double capacity; one is to provide that the cloths be truly dyed, and for that purpoſe to have them truly marked, to the end the people who buy them be not defrauded by ſuch practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as are before recited: the other is his care to ſee that the Subſidy be duely paid according to the Statute: for the Lawes do give unto the State a Subſidy of ſix pence, five pence, foure pence, three pence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:37276:38"/>to the colours put upon the cloths; as alſo the moiety of thoſe rates upon the halfe cloths: the ſame alſo is proportionably al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed upon ſtuffs: it is therefore apparent how neceſſary it is for the <hi>Aulnageor</hi> and his deputies to be knowingly converſant in colours alſo, and in the truth of dying, for as upon falſe made, and falſe aſſized cloths, his ſeale gives a great abuſe to the buyers, be they natives or forreigners; ſo the grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the States Armes to juſtifie falſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, cheats the Chapmen, whileſt both of them do diſhonour the Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of abuſes in exporting Wools and Fullers earth.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe whole world cannot produce ſuch accommodations for accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing the worke of clothing, as can the nation of <hi>England:</hi> for though moſt Countries do afford woolls, and thoſe of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:37276:39"/>
                  <hi>Spain</hi> are finer then in any other part of the world, yet will not thoſe of <hi>Spain</hi> ſort in worke with any other Nations, unleſſe it be theſe of <hi>England:</hi> a reaſon whereof may peradventure be, becauſe the <hi>Spaniſh woolls</hi> are grown originally from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſheep, which by that ſoyle, (reſemblant to the <hi>Downs</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) and by the elevation of the Pole for warmth, are come to that fineneſs; yet keep they a natural conjunction &amp; as it were, affection with theſe from whom they are deſcended: ſo we ſee the <hi>Wines</hi> of <hi>Canary</hi> which are planted from the grape of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> though they become much richer then thoſe of their naturall Climate, yet retain they the ſame flavor (as the <hi>Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> call it) with the <hi>Rheniſh,</hi> and before all other, do hold beſt with it in mixture: but to let paſſe compariſons, the wools of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are ſuperlatives to all the world for fineneſs, except that of the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> which neither by it ſelfe, nor by the incorporation with the wools of any other Nation, will be wrought into any cloth, without the help and mixture of <hi>Engliſh</hi> wools, which being
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37276:39"/>carded together (as by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clothi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers they are) they produce the richeſt manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures in clothing which the whole world can ſhew.</p>
               <p>Again, there is another materiall without which clothing cannot be perfected, which alſo in the excellency of it is onely appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to <hi>England,</hi> that is <hi>Fullers earth,</hi> without which clothing cannot be ſcow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the Seame and Oyles wherewith they muſt neceſſarily be wrought: It is poſſible and probable that other parts of the world may produce <hi>Fullers earth,</hi> but neither in ſuch fineneſſe nor abundance as this in <hi>England;</hi> which approbation is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirmed by the appraiſment which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> make of it, who ſpare not upon occaſion to give ten pounds <hi>ſterling</hi> a Tun for it, which any man may have in ſuch places as it growes, for three ſhillings the ſame quantity; ſurely this is a great tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to breake a commandement or Statute of Parliament, and ſo they do familiarly, as preſently ſhall appeare.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore to returne to the wools
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:37276:40"/>of this nation, ſuch as ſhall be pleaſed to peruſe the Statutes made in the beginning of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third his Reign, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite <hi>the tranſportation of raw wooll, white-Cloths, and Fullers earth,</hi> after that clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was confined to be made in <hi>England;</hi> ſhall find that the penalty which thoſe Lawes did inflict upon ſuch as ſhould break them, did extend to life or limb, at the <hi>Kings pleaſure, which of them he would pleaſe to take;</hi> for it is no more likely to make clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if the materials be carryed away, then it is to preſerve life without food, or government without power: true it is, that after clothing was ſetled, and that wools multiplyed beyond the Manufactures, then (with licenſe from the State) wools were permited to be tranſported, and by the like licenſe they have continued to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported; yet for the moſt part the State did ſtrictly regard the reſtraint, and in the chiefe liberty of exportation, the Grant was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted onely upon the meaner ſort of wools, and thoſe commonly from <hi>Ireland,</hi> where clothing might not be grieved.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:37276:40"/>
               <p> But the caſe is otherwiſe now, even in theſe dayes when clothing hath extended over this Land almoſt into every corner, when the great ſtrength of the Nation in people lyes upon the ſeverall relations to clothing; when the greateſt Cuſtoms and Revenue of the State ariſe from clothing; when the largeſt negotiation of merchandiſes over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreading the world, iſſueth from clothing; when the mightieſt power upon the Seas in Shipping growes from clothing; when the formidable obligation in awing all forreign States reſts upon clothing, even now is the practice and trade of tranſporting its mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls become almoſt an open profeſſion: and were this preſumption but as formerly the permiſſions, grants, and licenſes were, that is, upon the worſt wools onely, the faults were the leſſe; but theſe mens trade conſiſts of the beſt and fineſt wools, combd into <hi>Iarſies</hi> preſently fit for ſpinning, and theſe are contrived into Bales, as thoſe of Drapery, and entered into the Cuſtome-houſes, and ſhipt as clothing, and in all points ſo cunningly carryed as they are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:37276:41"/>diſcovered, and never ſeized as the Statutes do ſtrictly require.</p>
               <p>All States and Common wealths are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by two providentiall works, that is, <hi>Reward</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> for as no law can compell men to be corporally laborious, or ſtudious in knowledge of literature, unleſſe rewards be annex'd to all ſuch compulſions; ſo no providence can attend the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of profitable deſignes either in learning or trade, unleſſe puniſhments be enjoyned; this opinion that profound Senator <hi>Cicero</hi> alledgeth from <hi>Solon,</hi> one of the ſeven wiſe <hi>Graecians,</hi> and the onely man of them which gave Lawes; and this is the weake and frail eſtate of men and nations, that unleſſe they be as well encouraged in their endeavours, as puniſhed in their miſdemeanours, they will ſpeedily become Libertines and ruine all.</p>
               <p>Above three hundred yeares theſe works of clothing have been confined to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and untill late yeares have been ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, by the diligence of ſuch officers as have been ordained and empowred careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:37276:41"/>to ſee the manufactures kept under thoſe rules which the Lawes have provided for their perfection; amongſt which it muſt be concluded, that the materials were of eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall regard, which (as we have ſaid) are wools and Fullers earth: and ſeeing this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is by God peculiariſed in the ſe bleſſings and through the vigilancy of its Monarchs, ſafe guarded by Lawes, that the native ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures might not be undermined by the practiſes of forreigners, their ancient providence exacts from the preſent age the ſame preſervation, that thoſe particulars be not common to ſuch as daily labour to ſupplant the very being of this ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant trade, the negligence whereof hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready brought the Scales to an equality of the Beame betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> if rather the inclination tend not to their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
               <p>Again, we may be taught by their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, who ſpare no attendance in overſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſearching the true making of their manufactures, giving therefore power and commiſſions to perſons of more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:37276:42"/>worth amongſt them, whom they call <hi>Cure-maſters,</hi> which is Care-maſters, to whom every piece of worke of wools, be the condition of it what it will, is brought, opened, and ſurveighed from end to end, where the enquiry is not ſlight or ſhort, but theſe officers do unpartially examine it through all the hands it hath paſſed, even to the minglers of the wools, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards are carded, then ſpunne, ſo weaved, ſcowr'd, dyed, ſtrain'd, row'd, even from the firſt hand to the finiſhing of the Cloth: and where they find a defect, they make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault upon the cloth, which firſt is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed by a Fine to the State for abuſing the Lawes, and afterwards remaines to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh the buyer, who thereby may guard his purſe; and in caſe the Clothier be abuſed by any of his before-recited work-folks, he checques his dammage upon the true of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender in his wages, and all this is done to their own manufactures; but when the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines concernes <hi>Engliſh</hi> clothing, firſt, they load the cloth with Impoſts and Taxes, contrary to the Law of nations, and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37276:42"/>of the merchant, and afterwards are ſo rigorons in denoting faults upon it, as they oftentimes bring a great part of the price into taxes and abatements.</p>
               <p>The Premiſſes conſidered, let any man be Judge whether that Nation ought to be hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with the wools and Fullers earth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which they cannot worke, the exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which alſo is little leſſe then Felony in puniſhment, and of more dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage then ordinary Felonies, in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and compariſon of the crime; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe there is nothing which is prohibited to paſſe from <hi>England,</hi> more daily practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then theſe abuſes; yea, they are rather oppreſſions, and robberies of the greateſt magnitude.</p>
               <p>Nor is the tranſportation of theſe, in their loſſe, all the injury; but when honeſt men, well affected to the good of their Country, do detect theſe Caterpillers of the Common-wealth, who make ſo vaſt gaine as hath been denoted upon the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials ſo carefully prohibited, when they do endeavour by due courſe of Law to make
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:37276:43"/>ſtoppage thereof, and to have the offenders puniſhed, ſo many are the evaſions, ſuch combinations, and intereſt in the officers who ought to puniſh the offenders, ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour have they in Courts of Iuſtice, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions in the returne of Writs, and in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſuch affronts and diſcouragements, as the deareſt lover of his Country, or moſt intereſſed in Trade, dares not attempt to prevent that miſchief which his eyes behold to fall upon his nation, or which his owne perſon feeles to pick his pocket.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Concerning Apprentiſhips.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SUch is the pravity and weakneſs of mans nature, as without induſtry, art, and diſcipline, he remaines but the onely degree of Reaſon from a Beaſt: For as after the Creation of the firſt man, the worlds encreaſe and continuance of people hath by God himſelfe been eſtabliſhed by
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:37276:43"/>way of generation, ſo the arts of men and poliſhings of nature came firſt from God to man by ſome ſingular inſpirations to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain particular perſons, which afterwards continued amongſt men by nourtrature, education and diſcipline; the fundamentals of which are ſuperiority and inferiority, power and obedience, knowledge and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: now as the <hi>Iewes</hi> comprehended all the people of the world between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and <hi>Barbarians,</hi> ſo all conditions of men are compriſed between wiſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; this made <hi>Solomon</hi> ſay, <hi>That the Foole ſhall be ſervant to the wiſe in heart.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men learn not of men as beaſts do, barely to obey, but ſo to informe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as they may inſtruct them which come after, whereby even the world it ſelfe ſubſiſted, and muſt continue; that ſort of youth being moſt miſerable which wants education.</p>
               <p>There be, or ought to be in every parent two degrees of providence towards their children, one to have them live, the other to have them live well; nature hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37276:44"/>one, and inſtruction muſt give the other, which the Ancients and learned men call Diſcipline: not onely the Church and People of God from the Primitive times, have ordained this as a religious care, but the heathens, that is, the <hi>Perſians, Lacedemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Romans,</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> have framed Lawes, enjoyning Parents to inſtruct their children, and compelling children to obey their Parents on pain of death; which the weak and partiall affections of Parents neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting, the Common-wealth it ſelfe hath undertaken, and upon pious foundations have eſtabliſhed prudent Lawes, to the end Youth may be educated to the competent election of a vocation, anſwering their own genius and inclination, yet all this is but to ſolicite nature to perfect her own work, which muſt be done by Art, and Art is a worke of time, to which, that Youth may bequeath themſelves, the Lawes of each nation have proportioned a certain number of yeares, and that is generally ſeven.</p>
               <p>It is not without myſticall ſignification, that ſervitude is ſo generally faſtened upon
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37276:44"/>this number of ſeven yeares; <hi>Iacob</hi> cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted for ſeven yeares ſervice, and trebled them rather then he would not enjoy the freedome and purchaſe of that he ſo much loved and deſired; ſeven times ſeven yeares muſt paſſe before a Jubilee of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance could enfranchiſe offenders; the number of ſeven gave perfection and reſt to Gods workes: this number alſo is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monicall, compriſing all kinds of propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Arithmeticall, Geometricall, and Muſicall: It is the number of ſanctification, as may appeare in ſeverall paſſages of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Ceremoniall Law:</hi> it is the Climaterique, and conſummation of mans age: It is the compariſon of the moſt ſacred word of God, which <hi>David</hi> reſembles <hi>to ſilver ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventimes refined:</hi> it is alſo <hi>Solomons</hi> Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> ſupported by ſeven Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: and finally, to inſtance our own argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is the ternary ſeven of the age of Youth from the ſecond ſeven, which makes fourteen, to the third ſeven, which reacheth one and twenty; in which time the Braine, and Memory, beſt receive and retaine the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:37276:45"/>Inſtitutions, which that Party intends to follow in courſe of his nature, and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>There is a double reaſon why Youth is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in all Nations obliged to a ſeven years Apprentiſhip, before they can obtain a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to practice the Trade to which they are engaged: one is to teach the Diſciple or Apprentice; for ſuch is the dulneſſe of mans nature, that repetitions and multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of one and the ſame inſtruction, are little enough to faſten doctrines upon the judgment and memory of the learner, in matter of Art and Trade.</p>
               <p>The want of inſtruction and teaching in Clothing, is the principall cauſe that the Manufactures of wooll are ſo abuſively and deceptiouſly made; and teaching is thus wanting, becauſe there is no regular or legall courſe followed, either for time or form in working; there is not any of the relations to clothing which doth obſerve this rule of Apprentiſhip not withſtanding it is enjoyned in very ſtrict and penall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by the Statute Lawes; The chiefe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:37276:45"/>of which is, that a Trade ſo generall in uſe, and maintenance of even numberleſs Families, doth by its own vaſt exuberance convert into corruptions; and ſo thoſe great multitudes of People become diſcredited, begger'd, and finally ruined, to the deſtruction of themſelves, and that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which gave them ſo great a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               <p>Another prejudice, and not the leaſt, is, that the nation which hath given them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and inveſted them with ſuch materials for clothing, is diſhonoured by falſe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſive worke: &amp; it is not a little ſcandall to that nation, which God hath particularly endowed with thoſe bleſſings that others want, when its people ſhall divert thoſe good things which God hath beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, to evill and deceptious practiſes: In this conſideration it is very obſervable, how little comparatively, is the drunkeneſſe of thoſe Countries which produce wines, and wherein lyes their perſonall riches, and their Nations honour; Though their other ſinnes may ſufficiently ſwell their ultimate
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37276:46"/>account, yet doubtleſly it ſtrengthens their laſt apology, in that they abuſe not that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowment, which God hath made the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of their being and ſubſiſtence.</p>
               <p>A third conſideration is the cheat it puts upon all the world, for though every coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try have not the benefit of the Manufacture in themſelves, yet are there few of them condemned to ſuch ignorance, as not to diſcerne the Cozenage which falſe clothing puts upon them; in which caſe to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid diſhonour they adde a curſe; and it was a chiefe care in <hi>Iacobs</hi> practice for the bleſſing, <hi>that he turned it not into a curſe:</hi> how much more is this of conſideration, when the bleſſing comes by gift and not by deſign or procurement?</p>
               <p>And laſtly, great is the thought of heart, when the ſinnes of falſe lucre &amp; covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are in the ful purſuance of ſuch as have the full plenty to make weight and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet make it the art of their practice as wel as the practice of their art, to coſen both the wiſe and weake; it can be no great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, nor without abundance of Preſidents,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37276:46"/>if God for ſinnes of ſuch wilfullnes remove his bleſſings, with which this nation is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly enriched and dignified, and give them to a People which will render him a better, and more juſt, and more profitable accompt of his talent: and it is no newes, that though <hi>England</hi> be by the Almighty, chiefly ordayned to produce the materials, yet the manufactures be given to a people which will render a better account.</p>
               <p>All this, and much more is expected, if the Native people continue to abuſe the Native commodity, as of neceſſity they muſt, when they know not how to uſe it; the wiſdome of our Anceſtors hath been li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally manifeſted in this particular; for more or better Lawes are not ordained in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny relation to Trade, then that the manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors be conſtantly made Apprentiſes for ſeven yeares at leaſt, in ſtead of which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident ordination, there is not one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand made apprentice at all, but entering into Covenant with a workman in that he intends to profeſſe, after three or ſix months at the moſt, he leaps forth a workman for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:37276:47"/>his own account, and ſo brings his worke peradventure to the height of his Skill, which height is ignorance, and ſo the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are unremediable.</p>
               <p>The other reaſon, and yet untouch'd, why Apprentices are generally confined to ſeven yeares ſervitude, is to theend that in each art profeſſors multiply not beyond the ſupport of their trade, which were not to encreaſe good Subjects, but Vagabonds &amp; Rogues, to furniſh priſons &amp; the gallowes, which was not the intention of King <hi>Edw.</hi> the third, when in his deſign of bringing clothing into <hi>England,</hi> a chiefe part was ſo to multiply his People, as by his native and alleadgeate Subjects he might ſecurely poſſeſſe the Conqueſts wherewith God had bleſſed him, which were beyond any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prince of his time.</p>
               <p>It is utterly againſt reaſon that a nation can be poor, whoſe people are numerous, if their induſtries be compelled and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, and their idleneſſe be puniſhed and reformed; it is not the barrenneſſe of a Country which can forbid this maxime.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:37276:47"/>The <hi>Scots</hi> are an abounding and numberleſs people, and they have a Soyle which to a Travellers eye, ſeemes to produce nothing towards ſo vaſt a maintenance of the body of that People, yet are they in all parts of the world a warlike and honoured nation, helpfull to all Princes in their Warres, and readily upon occaſion returning to the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their brethren be their cauſe good or bad. The <hi>Dutch</hi> are a numerous Nation, daily multiplying in a Country which hath in compariſon, nothing of its own growth to ſupport them either in food or clothing, yet they want nothing either in neceſſaries or wealth, becauſe they are induſtrious; what Creeke of the Seas do they leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſited? And in Shipping are ſo ſtored, as moſt parts of the world do love or feare them.</p>
               <p>Now a great encreaſe of People reſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the regulation of Trade; for it is not the number of workemen, but the number of good workmen which encreaſeth Families; and it is Families which encreaſe and ſpread good people; the other for want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37276:48"/>and Skill, being fixed no where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their labours will not maintain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, much leſſe a family; for who will uſe a workman who hath neither Skill nor Credit, when he can employ one that hath both? Of principall importance therefore is the regulation of Apprentiſhips, both towards the beſt encreaſe of people, and to the honeſt, creditable, and wealthy manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures of woolls, and eſpecially of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; for want of which, not only the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer denoted defaults are daily found in their works, but good workmen are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſold and ruined by bad, and the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion involved in great diſhonour; therefore we will reſort to the Reformations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Shewing the abuſes of thoſe Lawes whereby Clothing ought to be remedyed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IUſtice (which all men cry up and few practice) is a vertue both divine and humane: Divine Juſtice is either from
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37276:48"/>God to man, wherein his Providence is his Juſtice, by which he governeth the world; or it is from man towards God, and then it is Piety, whereby he returnes to God praiſe and glory for his numberleſſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: In Republiques, Cities, and Townes, it is Equity, the fruit whereof is Peace and Plenty: In Domeſtique relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions between man and wife, it is unity and concord; from Servants to Maſters it is good-will and diligence; from maſters to ſervants it is humanity and gentleneſſe, and from a man towards his own body and ſoule, it is health and happineſſe; There is none of all theſe relations, but is neceſſary and important to the reformation of the abuſes, defaults, deceptions, and grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces committed upon clothing, which in this diſcourſe have been in ſome meaſure diſcovered, and by which both God and man are juſtly provoked.</p>
               <p>The juſtice we are to uſe to the reliefe of the complaints before exhibited is either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributive, or commutative; Juſtice diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butive is to give each man according to his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:37276:49"/>deſerts, whether it be honour or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and commutative juſtice, is in bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaining, bartering, exchanging, or in any tranſactions between man and man to keep promiſes, covenants, and contracts, and for a man to behave himſelfe as he would have others do unto him; to receive the innocent into protection, to repreſſe and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh offenders, without which, common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe and humane ſociety muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily be diſſolved, and for the preſervation whereof, amongſt the ancient Fathers have not ſpared their own ſonnes. The <hi>Egyptian</hi> Kings, to whom antiquity gives the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of making Lawes, did engage their Magiſtrates in an oath, that in Iudicature they ſhould reſiſt any unjuſt Commands even from their Princes themſelves: The <hi>Graecians</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> deified Iuſtice, and would not violate it towards their enemies; ſo juſt alſo were the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> and ſo free from diſtruſting each other, as even for the publique ſafety they uſed neither locks nor barres; inſomuch that one asking <hi>Archidamus</hi> who thoſe Governours were
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:37276:49"/>which ſo juſtly, happily, and gloriouſly, governed the Common wealth of <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> anſwered, that they were firſt the Lawes, and afterwards the Magiſtrates exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting thoſe Lawes; for Law is the rule of Juſtice, and Juſtice is the end of the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rectum eſt index ſui &amp; obliqui,</hi> a right Line doth not onely juſtify it ſelfe, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth the crooked, ſay the <hi>Mathematicians;</hi> by which it may ſeeme, that the ready way to rectify abuſes about clothing, were to compare them with the Rule of the Lawes provided for them, which nevertheleſſe holds not in all points; for inſtance, the Law empowers the Merchants and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to be their own Searchers, and to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Clothiers purſe, as they find his works to be faulty; and ſo they do, to the no ſmall griefe of the Clothier: but <hi>cui bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no?</hi> For the retayling buyer is not hereby at all relieved, the Draper ſelling to him thoſe faults for which he was before paid by the Clothier; the Merchants do the ſame, by cauſing their Clothiers to bring their manufactures into the Merchants
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:37276:50"/>private Ware houſes, where their own ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants are Judges, who upon ſearching the Clothes do make, and marke faults enough, for which they have reparable abatements, but themſelves again do practice all fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wayes they can to barter and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change thoſe faults away, without giving any allowance for them; and though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they be detected, yet find they means to ſave their purſes, whileſt their Nation ſuffers in honour, and the Lawes are vilified to Forreigners, who ſtain the Juſtice of the Nation with weaknes and fraud: true it is that in the Netherlands, where their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is as piercing, as their practiſe is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, they (even every buyer) do ſearch with diligence, and make themſelves repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, firſt to the Merchants great loſſe, and ſo in courſe to the Clothiers no ſmall dammage: but in all this the State remains much diſhonoured by the ſcandall, and robb'd of thoſe Fines which the Lawes in puniſhment do give to the publique Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, which if they were rightly and legally attended, would render a vaſt gain to the Common wealth.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:37276:50"/>
               <p> As in diſeaſes where the cauſes are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the remedies are conſequently miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, whereby a diſeaſe in ſuppoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes one in fact; ſo in the foregoing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the remedies being miſapplyed, are themſelves brought to be a diſeaſe almoſt incureable: therefore though in finding out the cauſes why manufacture in clothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſo abuſed, there may be good uſe of the Drapers &amp; Merchants knowledge and Skill, yet the application of the remedy is a worke of State and Policy, in making and executing the Lawes proportionably to the grievance, in which inſtance it doth not hold; for though the Merchants and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers be able Searchers of the abuſes, yet they are not competent reformers of the grievances, becauſe they are intereſſed in participating of thoſe gaines which the faults occaſion and intend.</p>
               <p>Nor is this all the abuſe, for in ſuch parts of the world as the buyers are not in ability of knowledge, like the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who make Cloths themſelves, and eſpecially in thoſe parts where the difference in Religion is ſo
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:37276:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>great as it is between Chriſtians and Turks, there the corrupt Merchant cauſeth the name of God to be blaſphemed; for when thoſe people, whoſe eye and judgment gives them not ſo good information as doth their proofe and wearing, do find themſelves cheated in their garments, they preſently conclude, that there is no feare of God in that place, nor obedience to their Rulers for conſcience, which muſt aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly procure much ſcandall to Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>Now as <hi>Pliny</hi> obſerves (as in the Front you have it) that <hi>Pecunia dicitur à Pecude,</hi> thereby bringing the originall of mony from ſheep; affirming that the ancient ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature upon money was a ſheep; he alſo thereby ſhewes that merchandiſes were the cauſe of money, and there being no greater merchandiſes then are from the ſheep, he makes it evident that there is nothing more requiſite towards the enriching this nation, whoſe peculiar bleſſing reſts in ſheep, then ſtrictly to hold the manufactures to the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and rule provided for their juſt making,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:37276:51"/>and that the lawes be unpartially executed; For, <hi>Neceſsarium illud dicitur ſine quo fieri non poteſt,</hi> and it being apparent that this Nation cannot be rich without a conſtant utterance of clothing, nor can that be done without a perfect reformation in the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the works, it doth undeniably follow, that clothing muſt be purged from its corruptions, or <hi>England</hi> muſt be poore: It is therefore the Manufactors which abuſe the woolls, and thereby improvidently give advantage to the <hi>Dutch;</hi> whereas a perfection in the making of Cloths in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> will gainfully underſell the <hi>Hollander</hi> a Noble in a Pound ſterling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Shewing how the Lawes are uſed to croſse and deſtroy each other about clothing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY that which hath been ſaid, it doth appear that there may be too much Law, though there cannot be too
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:37276:52"/>much juſtice, and where the Law abuſeth juſtice, that Common wealth is in a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate condition: <hi>England</hi> will be found in little better ſtate, if a ſhort review be taken of ſome preceding paſſages: for the Lawes are made to fight againſt themſelves in that tedious cont roverſie about the <hi>Aulnageors</hi> Subſidy: for though there be none more authentique then ſuch as eſtabliſh that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, nevertheleſſe the litigations about the legality of this Subſidy, and the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the State revenue hath for ſome late yeares been carryed on with ſuch heat, as ſome innocent officers for doing their duty, have been no leſſe then ruined: For which cauſe the deputies and ſubſervient Aulnageors become very remiſſe in their office, as well in ſelling their Seales by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens to ſuch as will buy them (the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience and loſſe whereof is formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared) as by neglecting to ſurvey and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine what clothes are Statutable or truly ſealed: Again the Farmers and ſub-farmers of the Aulnage, being (through the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and interrupting their ſervants) made
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:37276:52"/>unable to pay their Rents, the Leſſors to them ever premiſing a Clauſe in their Leaſe for re-entry upon non-payment of their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted Rent, do preſently upon default grant a new Leaſe to another man utterly unknown to the preceding Tenant; by which promiſcuous courſe there are divers <hi>Aulnageors</hi> for one and the ſame place, at one and the ſame time; whereof the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier ſoon getting knowledge, by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing a double duty, he payes to neither, yet gets his Clothes ſealed by ſuch indirect meanes as is before declared; in all which proceedings, the Law is abuſed under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of legality.</p>
               <p>As for the duty of ſearching, the former powers granted by that Statute of <hi>quarto Iacobi</hi> to the Merchants and Drapers, and the inconveniences thereupon denoted, are enough to ſhew the Imperfections of that Statute to that uſe; nevertheleſſe not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the prejudice to the buyer, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Nation, are thereby as it were authorized, but the loſſe to the State is not eaſily to be valued, ſeeing that in that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:37276:53"/>Country of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> the taxes or abatements for defects in Clothing have been by that State puniſhed to the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of ten thouſand pounds in one yeare; what then muſt be the Income of the like abuſes upon the whole clothing of <hi>England</hi> in thoſe Fines which the Statutes give to the State? all which are loſt for want of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſearches, where the faults being dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and marked upon the edges of the Clothes, as the Statutes require, all future buyers are ſatisfyed of their worth, and the State ſecured of the revenue: and that theſe faults cannot be few, the Reader may be pleaſed to caſt his eye over their works, in mingling, carding, ſpinning, weaving, ſcowring, milling, rowing, tentering, and many other works, wherein every one helps his Lawfull living by unlawfull practices. True it is, that the foreſaid Statute of <hi>quarto Iacobi,</hi> by the largeneſſe of it ſeemes to be an epitome of all the Statutes made in three hundred yeares before; yet ſuch are the inſufficiencies, and the incongruities of the commands, and powers thereby eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:37276:53"/>as the Subject, and more eſpecially Forreigners are rather grieved then relieved by it, wherein the diſhonour of the State and Nation is very great and apparent.</p>
               <p>Now for the weight of Clothes ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely commanded, and by the Statute ſtrictly enjoyned, the Clothiers are herein generally abuſive; for whereas they were originally ordained to weigh ſixty foure pounds a Cloth, and afterwards by degrees came to fifty eight, yet now for want of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act ſearching they hold themſelves very o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to the Law, when their Clothes hold fifty ſix pounds a piece, whereof more come ſhort then over, their generall anſwer being, that they cannot caſt their Clothes in a mould, yet when they pleaſe they wil bring twenty Clothes together not differing from each others weight ſo much as a quarter of a pound in a Cloth, ſo as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed one may judge that they were caſt in a mould, which men could as well make them hold as neare to fifty eight pounds; but herein lyes the Weavers chief practice of falſhood, for they will many times make
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:37276:54"/>them foure or ſix pound ſhort of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes eſtabliſhed weight, and then they find tricks with Stones, Leaden weights, and the like ponderous things to give them weight, which upon the <hi>Aulnageors</hi> legall ſearch, may ſoon be diſcovered and ſeized.</p>
               <p>Again, the Law is by the Law croſſed and abuſed even in thoſe places where they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend they have legall eſtabliſhed Searchers; firſt in their number, there ought to be ſix or eight in a towne, according to the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the Corporation, and clothing in it: ſecondly, thoſe Searchers ought to give ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of fourty pounds penalty at the leaſt, and to approve themſelves men of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, wealth, and integrity, to the end the ſearch may be throughly performed once in a month or oftner: and they are by the Law furniſhed with power to carry their ſearch through Warehouſes, Shops, Ships, or any other place which ſhall harbour any clothing or manufactures ſearchable, the reſiſtance or concealment whereof, is put under ſtrict and valuable penalty: thirdly, they are by the Sature appointed in their
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:37276:54"/>Search what faults to denote, and what pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties to declare on each fault.</p>
               <p>In performance of which Injunctions, firſt, out of townes Corporate there is no Searcher appointed, but all is left at liberty to the Clothier, who uſeth his liberty ſo much to his own advantage, as ſhould a Searcher be there eſtabliſhed by a Iuſtice of Peace, as the Law requires, he ſhall aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly be affronted, ſued, and impriſoned by ſuch ſecret helps as the Clothier can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in the Exchequer, carrying therewith ſuch abuſive countenance of the Law, as a ſingle and ſimple Officer dares not reſiſt. Secondly, in Townes Corporate, where this office ought to be attended with num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, there is ſometimes none, but never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove one, and that an ignorant man, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo both nominated and ſworn by the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, who undoubtedly is ever a Clothier, and as likely by his power to be an offender, whom ſuch a worthleſſe officer as himſelfe puts in, dares not controule, much leſſe correct or ſeize his Clothes: Adde to this alſo, that as he is an abject perſon, and the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:37276:55"/>creature of the Magiſtrate, ſo is he wanting in knowledge to judge of good and true worke, as alſo of eſtate or ability to anſwer his neglects, or to give ſecurity therefore.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, there is neither fault nor penalty denoted, or put upon the Seale or Cloth, wherein the State is abundantly damnified: but becauſe in ſuch a conſtant practice it is impoſſible but ſome people muſt be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and ſome clothes ſeized, in ſuch caſes another law appeares (in oppoſition to the Statute which directs the deciding and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging ſuch faults to the Lord Treaſurer) by which the Magiſtrate of the place where ſuch ſeizure is made, takes upon him more then the Lord Treaſurer, for he not onely condemnes the culpable goods, but <hi>ex offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio,</hi> he appropriates the confiſcation to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>If in Villages there be a Searcher eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the Juſtice (as the Law enjoynes) then ſuch ſeizures come to the Quarter Seſſions, where by favour and friendſhip the offender eſcapes, and the State is the fufferer: in a word, it is very materiall to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:37276:55"/>obſervation, that of ſo many thouſands of Clothes as are made defective and decepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> the Exchequer neither ſees one Cloth ſo ſeized or ſeizable, no nor a Penny for all the Fines or redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a Cloth, but the abuſes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, increaſe, and are maintained, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth and forreigners are generally wronged, the State is deprived of its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, even to vaſt ſummes, the Nation is diſhonoured over all the world, and the continuance of it, if not ſpeedily reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will plead preſcription.</p>
               <p>We will now walk through the Meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers office, who (ſince the Aulnageor left it) is ordained by the Statute to be ſworne in Corporations by the Magiſtrate, and in Villages by the Juſtice adjacent, but no Law allowes either them to nominate or appoint the ſaid officer; yet in Corporations it is ſo ordered, as well to the Subjects, as to the Forreigners great dammage, whereof daily preſidents may be produced: out of Corporations there is no ſuch officer; which defect the Clothiers as well as others do
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:37276:56"/>feele; In which proceedings there is alſo Law againſt Law; Firſt, in Corporations where the <hi>Aulnageor</hi> ought by the Law to preſent his deputies, to whom the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is bound under the Penalty of five pounds to give an oath, there the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate finds a Law to claim both, &amp; therein proceeds as he did about the Searcher, which is formerly related; and out of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations there is Law againſt Conſcience, where the Clothiers for want of a legall Meaſurer, do bring them unmeaſured to <hi>London,</hi> and becauſe they dare not ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the Market, the Lord Mayor, <hi>ex officio,</hi> cauſeth his ſworn Meaſurer to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them, yet the Clothier for his private ſatisfaction cauſeth them to be moſt exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meaſured before he brings them from home; nevertheleſſe he receives them again from the aforeſaid ſworn Meaſurers hands, with the ordinary loſſe of foure, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſix yards in a piece, of which abuſe, the Day men in <hi>Eſsex</hi> make no ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint.</p>
               <p>The Mill-men and Cloth-workers can
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:37276:56"/>find ſmall colour of Law to countenance their misbehaviours, yet they ſpare not to practcie their deceptions, and becauſe they have no ſhadow of Law, they find out the more Art to keep their Cheats from diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, which through uſe and continuance are now become the chief ſecret and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, yea the principall part of their trade, (there being very few able to make a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Cloth.) There be indeed ſome caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which are pardonable, as heate in the Mill to the prejudice of a Cloth which goes in too dry; ſome come by ſmall ſtones un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerned in the Fulling-earth; ſome oyles change colour, and alter the cloth, and ſome other there be of ſuch kinds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:37276:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>The croſſing of the Law by their own Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, in exporting raw wools, Fullers earth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN this part of our complaint, wee preſume not to meddle with Licences granted by the State to export Raw wools, or white Clothes, both of which have been permitted to paſſe the Seas, as well for the good of the People, as for the benefit of Clothing it ſelfe, yet ſo as to have the ſame limited, and joyned with the tranſportation of coloured Clothes, may be found much to the advantage of the Nations commodity in Clothing: and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to obſerve times in ſuch Licences is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry requiſite; for many Acts of Parliament (uſefull and important without doubt to the good of the publique when they were ordained) have nevertheleſſe within few yeares following, not onely been ſuſpended but repealed; in which condition the ſtate
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:37276:57"/>of white Clothes hath been ſometimes found; at preſent the liberty is great, and and thought to be good, converting to the utility of the Merchant adventurers, but (without deniall) it is a great prejudice to the Dyers, and therein to many thouſands of People: As for Raw Wools there may be advantage to the Common wealth by their exportation, namely, when the Cloth trade is obſtructed, and the manufactures lye upon the Clothiers hand, which at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is ſo found, both by the troubles of the Seas, and the daily Warres, which ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the utterance of Cloth, leaves the wool upon the Graſiers hands, and extends to the prejudice of almoſt all the People of <hi>England:</hi> nevertheleſſe ſuch as can find a market for Wools, may if they pleaſe, find the ſame for Clothes, and therefore they are fit to paſſe together, ſo as the wools in ſmaller quantity, may help off the Clothes in greater meaſure.</p>
               <p>The place alſo to which Wools may be licenſed to paſſe, ought to be conſidered, and that may rather be any where then the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:37276:58"/>
                  <hi>Netherlands,</hi> where their whole drift is to undermine the Engliſh Cloth-trade, which they cannot ſo profitably accompliſh, if they be forced to procure the wools through many hands and ſeverall voyages: by no meanes therefore is the preſent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice to be borne, which daily carrieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the fineſt ſorts of Wools ready combed into Jarſies for worke, which they pack up as Bales of Cloth, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they do enter and Cuſtome them: Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for Fullers earth, there is never any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion why that ſhould be tranſported, therefore to have it licenced either by its own name, or by that of Tobbaco-pipe-earth, or by any other title, is clearly the greateſt injury which can be done to Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: It is a commodity which the <hi>Dutch</hi> cannot get in any quantity, or worth, nearer then the Streights, unleſſe from Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, where the totall exportation being by the Statutes moſt ſtrictly prohibited, their clothing being the more laden with charge, the Engliſh will be better able to underſell them.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:37276:58"/>
               <p> Now to ſhew the Reader how the Lawes are croſſed and daily obſtructed to ſuch as endeavor to ſerve their Country, by ſuch as ought to encourage the Proſecutors; ſurely there will be very many practices of evill conſequence diſcovered: for firſt, in the Cuſtome-houſes where Bonds are taken to the intent theſe prohibited commodities paſſe not by meanes of Marriners out of the Nation, but onely from Port to Port, for accommodation of ſuch parts as want ſuch commodities, they are very remiſſe and careleſſe in taking account of the Sea-mens diſcharge of their obligatory conditions, where alſo it is uſuall with the Sea men to bring fraudulent Certificates, and ſo do cheate the States providence, who keep ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants at great wages purpoſely to prevent ſuch abuſes; or if there be a regular returne of the Bonds, yet there is commonly a frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulency in giving them, for the Maſters of Ships will ſo contrive their deſigne, as he who is Maſter at giving the Bond, and is le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally bound, ſhall immediately paſſe his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to another man, who taking charge
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:37276:59"/>of the Veſſell and Voyage, is notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not engaged in the Port-Bonds, and therefore neither is he accountable for breach of their condition: Again, when the Port-Bonds are juſtly taken, and as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly returned, yet to prevent the true and real detection of the offender, and to diſhearten the legall Proſecutor, ſome friend of the offenders will clap in an information a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, purpoſely to hinder and divert others, and ſoon after will let the proſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on fall at his pleaſure; nay, it hath been ſaid, and peradventure not unjuſtly, that ſuch preventing Informations have been anteda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to the overthrow of the reall informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; But when all is granted, and a full and formall hearing and Decree paſſed to the juſt condemnation of the offender, yet when Judgments and Enquiries are gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and do without Errours of the Clerks, (which is not alwayes) empower the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs and their Bayliffs to ſee execution thereof made, it is familiar with thoſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers to return a <hi>Noneſt inventus,</hi> or a <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus eſt,</hi> even then when the offender and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:37276:59"/>the officer have been known to be drinking together at that very time when the Writ ſhould have been executed.</p>
               <p>After all this, one ſtep further will ſhew how charity it ſelfe abuſeth Juſtice; for let all the former proceedings be granted to be candid and cleare, and that the Law be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed juftly and legally executed, the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in cuſtody, and nothing remaining but that he honeſtly diſcharge himſelfe with money, (ſeeing baile will not be admitted) nevertheleſſe upon a lamenting Petition, and urging a great charge of children to the Bench, the offender is uſually admitted to compound for ten in the hundred, or leſſe, when by his offence he hath gained a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred for ten, or more, and peradventure hath undone a hundred Families in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet all this while the honeſt Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the onely man that appeares for the good his of country, who ought by the law to have the full benefit and advantage of the Law <hi>gratis,</hi> it being enough that he ſpends his time for promotion of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique weale, after it hath coſt him ſeverall
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:37276:60"/>great ſummes of Money, and large expence of time to bring the offence to Triall and Conviction, is diſmiſſed with little or no ſatisfaction, unleſſe he be rewarded with the Brand of an informing Knave; ſurely they who made theſe Lawes for the benefit of themſelves and their Country, did intend a more currant and juſt paſſage towards them, then thus to be obſtructed and baffled; But at the preſent time <hi>Felis dormit, et mures ſaltant,</hi> every man doth as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; Proſecutors and Informers have paid for their Learning, that it is better to loſe a Coate then a Skinne: ſuch abuſes as theſe made <hi>Theodorus</hi> ſay, as in the Preface you have it, that a Wiſeman did himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, by hazarding his wiſdome and eſtate for the benefit of his Nation; and therefore ſome have not ſpared to urge, that Cuſtoms and Impoſts, and Tolls and Taxes, might be taken away from honeſt, laborious, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous Trades and Adventurers, and be put upon litigious Suites at Law, and ſuch as make benefit of their corrupt breath, that is to ſay, upon ſuch Lawyers as abuſe their
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:37276:60"/>Clients, and ſuch malicious Clients as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the name of a juſt and innocent defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant; but righteouſneſſe muſt be expected in another world, for in this he that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to remove diſcommodities, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences from the Lawes, doth under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to cut off <hi>Hydra's</hi> heads, ſaith divine <hi>Plato,</hi> which <hi>Seneca</hi> cofirmeth in ſaying, <hi>Nullum ſine auctoramento eſt malum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. <hi>Containing ſome Queries of Remedies.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have ſeen a ſhort account of ſome abuſes in relation to clothing; to ſpeake of all the frauds and deceptions daily practiced about theſe manufactures, were in ſubſtance to fil a volume, they being for invention far beyond the compaſs of one mans brain: but becauſe it is concluded to be more eaſie to extinguiſh another mans vertue, then to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a mans owne; it will here be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:37276:61"/>that ſome meanes ſhould be propoſed by way of reformation, proportionable to the offences and grievances related.</p>
               <p>A Ship is one of the moſt excellent ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures both for wealth, and fafety, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, that ever was invented; yet that vaſt Body, that Magazine of wealth, that Caſtle of ſtrength would be of no uſe, were it not for that ſmall timber the Rudder, which contracting as it were all the Mathematicall lines of the Hulls compoſition, every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion anſwers in obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and checques of that inconſiderable <hi>Moover,</hi> the <hi>Rudder.</hi> It is ſo in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which therefore magnifies Monarchy or ſingle Dominion, for though the Art of man might frame two or more Rudders to one Ship, yet all the wiſdome of man could not ſo proportion the obedience of the Veſſell, but that there would be diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the courſe and ſayling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foelix qui potuit rerum cognoſcere cauſas,</hi> and though it be more eaſie to derive the errours then to contrive the remedies, yet it is a great ſtep towards health for a man
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:37276:61"/>to know the cauſe of his ſicknes; and it may be concluded, that he who hath taken the paines to give himſelfe knowledge of the ſeverall abuſes ariſing upon ſo immenſe a worke as Clothing is, would not trouble his Countrymen with relation of their grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, unleſſe he knew likewiſe how to ſhape the remedyes in proportion to them; If the Reformation did reſt onely upon the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the reſpective Statutes provided for them may ſeem to expedite that worke, but ſo many have been the inventions to carry theſe offences beyond the reach of theſe Statutes, that the reformation by them is not probable, whileſt they diſagree ſo in themſelves,</p>
               <p>In the firſt place therefore we preſent the the Lawes themſelves to conſideration, which are ſo, and ſo often uſed and mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged one againſt another, as they may well admit a reconciliation, which is ſuppoſed to be moſt properly the work of the learned Judges, or elſe of a Parliament if it be ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and herein the firſt difference of note is, that of ſo long and great heate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:37276:62"/>between the old and new Draperies, wherein (if the queſtion be not already reſolved by the ancient Judges, as is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed) it remaines to be enquired <hi>why that Subſidy was granted, and upon what Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factures it was granted, and what it was that was granted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>thoſe Queries once reſolved, and the Law being ſet cleare from ſuch bold</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitors, <hi>it is next to be vertuated by the power and countenance of the State; and that the</hi> Aulnageor <hi>who is truſted with ſo honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a charge as is the Seal of the State, (which the Law requires him to uſe to the juſtice of the People, the advantage of the publique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, and to the honour of the Nation) may be ſo countenanced and encouraged as a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Juſtice, and the dignity pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>per to ſuch truſts do require, and by no meanes to be affronted in the execution of his office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>That it be reſolved whether ths Magiſtrates in Corporations (who are alwayes men dealing in Clothing) ought both to nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the Perſons, and to adminiſter the Oath, to the Searchers and Meaſurers of Clothing,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:37276:62"/>and if not, who then ought to nominate or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thoſe officers to the Magiſtrates, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are bound under a penall ſumme to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster the ſaid Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>whether the Clothing which is now diſperſed all over this Nation, as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out as within Corporations, may be ſearched and meaſured at thoſe rates of allowance which the Statutes provided when Clothing was confined to Corporations onely, or whether the neglect for want of a competent Salary, hath not been a great cauſe to let in manifold abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon Clothing. Which being granted, the next enquiry is, what ſhall be the Salary, and by whom it ſhall be paid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>that in regard the manufactures of Clothing are by the Statutes confined to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations, and nevertheleſſe are (through Gods great bleſsing) ſo multiplied as the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations cannot contain them, whether the Clothing which is made in Villages, may not by the power of the State, be brought to ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent villages or market townes, lying conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently for their tranſportation to Markets, and there to be ſearch'd, meaſur'd, weighd, &amp;
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:37276:63"/>ſealed, provided the ſame be within fifteene miles off the Clothiers habitation, and whether in every ſuch town it may not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to erect Halls, and therein to place Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Pearches, Scales, Weights, and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, for the better diſcharging the ſaid du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and benefit of the Clothiers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, <hi>whether the reformation of colours and dying be not belonging to the</hi> Aulnageor, <hi>in regard the Law gives him cognizance, and ſubſidy upon the ſaid colours, and whether the prohibitions and ſearches for</hi> Block-wood, Logwood, <hi>and other forbidden materials do not belong, or are fiting to relate to the</hi> Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageors <hi>charge, who in regard of the ſubſidy is to ſee that the grounds of colours be juſtly and truely laid, to the laſting of the colours, advantage of the cloth, and to the honour and profit of the State.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, <hi>whether it be not requiſite that the two principall materialls belonging to clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (which are</hi> Wools <hi>and</hi> Fullers-earth) <hi>for prevention of their illegall tronſportati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ought not moſt properly to be within the care and charge of the</hi> Aulnageor, <hi>and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:37276:63"/>ſome ſpeedy and ſtrict courſe ought not to be taken with offenders herein, to prevent their evaſions and abuſes of the Lawes in that caſe provided, and whether the intuition of the ſame belong not most properly to the</hi> Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageor?</p>
               <p>Eighthly, <hi>whether all thoſe trades which are appertaining to any manufactures of wools, as</hi> Minglers, Carders, Spinners, Weavers, Fullers, Cloth workers, <hi>and the like, ought not to be attended with ſervants of ability and good knowledge, for which each of the ſaid ſervants ought by injunction of the Law, and many ſtrict Statutes to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to be bound Apprentices, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the number of ſeven yeares in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſaid knowledge; and whether it be not proper to have the ſaid Apprentices bound, enrolled, and enfranchiſed in the Halls before named, to the end that falſe and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant work men be not admitted to abuſe both Natives and Forreigners as they have done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ninthly, <hi>whether all commodities coming from forreign parts, and meaſurable, be not properly belonging to the charge of the</hi> Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageor,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:37276:64"/>
                  <hi>as in King</hi> Edward <hi>the ſeconds time they were, and in ſome other Kings Reignes both before and ſince they have been, to the intent the native Subjects be not abuſed, as at this day is found in abundance, and whether a Fee for ſo doing be not in the power of the State, for the viſible benefit of the People, it being eſtabliſhed in proportionable manner to the workes as we daily find it to be done in other States.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tenthly, <hi>whether the Manufactures of</hi> Cotton wooll, <hi>converted into</hi> Ticking, Fuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, <hi>and the like merchantable commodities, ought not to be within the ſurvey of the</hi> Aulnageor, <hi>or if not, then in whoſe power it is to regulate the ſaid manufactures, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard they are at preſent much altered and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted from their primitive ordination both in length and breadth; and whether likewiſe the State may not impoſe a Fee upon thoſe workes as in other clothing is done, to the end the natives be not abuſed as now they are.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we have proceeded upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of ſome abuſes, being no ſmall grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, as alſo by an humble inquiſition
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:37276:64"/>into ſome remedies, both of which may be enlarg'd as occaſion and encouragement do invite; for it is not enough thus briefly and ſuperficially to runne over misdemeanours, and reformations, where the worke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to the univerſall good or ill of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no more then it is to take a generall ſurvey upon an entire and compacted bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to diſcover the diſeaſes of all bodies; but when the Limbs, and Veines, and Nerves, and Arteries, when the noble parts, the heart, the braine, the liver of one man come to be diſſected, the Anatomy will then ſhew the infirmities and diſorders which have brought that body, and by the ſame occaſions, may bring others into a finall diſſolution: nevertheleſſe the reſult in clothing will not be like the ſimilitude in diſeaſes; for by the inſpection of one body many may be cured, but if Clothing muſt dye, (as it is likely to do) for want of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the remedies, how then ſhall clothing be found again in this Nation to undergo the cure?</p>
               <p>It is not of ſmall importance therefore
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:37276:65"/>well to conſider the preſent ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of clothing, for though the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls be Engliſh, yet they have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times converted into clothing in other Countryes; and peradventure upon an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious and diligent inquiſition, it may be found, that there was not more art and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy uſed in bringing home the worke to the Wooll, then now there is cunning and daily practices to carry the native materials unto forreign manufactures; to the helpe whereof, and in apology for il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legall clothing, every man holds himſelfe juſtified by the newneſſe of the invention; but if the Lawes for regulation muſt be bound to attend the Lawes for invention, it will prove not onely the greateſt but the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſtruction to the ancient and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Clothing, by degenerating into fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall and invalid inventions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:37276:65"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of the benefits of Clothing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough all that hath been ſaid, hath been delivered with integrity as to truth, and with affection in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to this Nation, yet the Author flatters not himſelfe that he hath pleaſed all his Countrymen, for he expecteth oppoſers, and wiſheth for them, if their intent and purpoſe be (as his is) to the good of his native Country; for ſo <hi>Contraria inter ſe poſita magis eluceſcunt,</hi> and there is no doubt of a publique benefit where all men endeavour it: To the end therefore that God may have his due praiſe and glory for his immenſe goodneſs and bleſſing beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that peculiar of wooll upon this Nation, we will conclude the whole with a ſhort Survey of ſome particular immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which clothing hath conferred upon <hi>England,</hi> with which the glory of it extends to the Verges and utmoſt inhabited parts
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:37276:66"/>of the world, and without which the Arke of Gods mercy and the glory of this Land is like to depart.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the reducing of clothing to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in manufacture as well as in materials; (which muſt a thouſand times repeate <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> gratitude to the memory of that ever renowned King <hi>Edward</hi> the third) hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſuch opulent and magnificent Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Merchants, as the whole world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not againe demonſtrate, that is to ſay, firſt the Merchant Adventurers Company, whoſe Governours, Preſidents, Conſulls, and the like chiefe officers are not of leſſe eſteeme (where they pleaſe to ſeat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) then are the Reſidentiaries of the greateſt Princes; and ſo much the more cordiall is their welcome, as each mans profit leads his affection beyond his reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to publique Embaſſies, becauſe proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to a mans perſonall intereſt ſits nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in his thoughts, then when he is invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the publique concernment.</p>
               <p>This Company hath by their Policy, and Order, ſupplanted thoſe Societies of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:37276:66"/>the <hi>Hans</hi> Townes, (as they are called) who vending an inconſiderable number of cloths and at low rates, did nevertheleſſe account England obliged to them for their Markets and Shipping; whereas at this day the Merchant Adventurers do utter ten times as many cloths annually in the ſame mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, at farre better prices, and in anſwer to the Shipping which England had in thoſe times from thoſe Countries at deare enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment: This trade of clothing, and this particular company of Merchants, have furniſhed the Navy-Royall from time to time, and upon all occaſions with ſuch ſtrengths, as they have not feared, (if they have not awed) the greateſt Navall Forces ſayling upon the Ocean; he that may have the favour to peruſe their Records ſhall find what opportune ſervice they did for their Country in the yeare eighty eight, and ſince upon all military occaſions wherein this Nation hath been embroyled with any other.</p>
               <p>Next, the Eaſt land Company hath plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the trade of Clothing all about the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:37276:67"/>Seas, which at this day employes many warlike Ships, and gives a great encreaſe of Marriners, to the no ſmall growth of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands ſtrength at Sea: The <hi>Muſcovia</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany have diſcovered the paſſage by the North Cape, and the great trade of Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; what wealth accrews to England by the <hi>Turkey</hi> and <hi>Eaſt Indian</hi> Companies is not eaſie to be numbered, their Shipping alſo being as ſtrong and rich as any that ſwimme upon the Seas: how one of them hath by the trade of Cloth onely, engroſſed all manner of wealth coming from the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant-Seas, and how the other of them hath eſtabliſhed the rich Trades of Silks, Spices, Jewels, &amp;c. in the Southern parts of the world, is by all admired, though by none to be valued; and what ſtrengths of Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping theſe two Companies have produced, as they have been wonderfull, ſo they have been formidable to al Nations: what contri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bution the clothing Trade with <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> have given to Englands maritime powers, is by thoſe Countryes themſelves feared, as well as by England found to its great ſecurity.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:37276:67"/>
               <p> And as theſe unvaluable bleſſings have befallen England by the trade of Clothing, politiquely and providently drawn into So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, Companies and Corporations; ſo the looſe tranſactions of trade in other Countryes have rendered them ſo poore at Sea, as were it not for the Shipping of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Holland, the very life of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce would periſh, would returne to the ſame wilderneſs and uſeleſneſſe as it is now in Greenland, and the Weſt India, where Civill Government hath not once beene heard of.</p>
               <p>Again, if compariſon be made for rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Trade, between Clothing and any, or all other ſubſtances of Merchandiſes, whereby any Nation, but more eſpecially England may be enriched; neither the Silks, nor Furres, nor Wines, nor Spices, nor Bullion it ſelfe of all other Countries can render that account to its own, or can in proportion equalize England in Clothing, Food, Shipping, Strength of People, or wealth of Money, the honour whereof, rightly derived muſt (next after that which
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:37276:68"/>in all Ages hath been and is due to the State for its providence) reſt upon the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Adventurers, upon whom neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there have been, and at this preſent are, great oppreſſions and Impoſitions, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoſe of Holland, whereof we here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare particularly to enlarge, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined this briefe Diſcourſe to the Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound grievances of England, yet ſo as we intend not to ſmother thoſe juſt complaints of forreign abuſes, which together with ſome other irregularities of Trade, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain humble preſentments of Reformation, ſhal hereafter attend the preſent acceptance of this ſmall offering; in purſuance whereof peradventure upon Conference with ſome of the many Lawes which the ſeverall Kings and Queenes of this Nation have in Parliaments enacted for the advance and wealth of Trade, ſomething more then is at preſent in viſibility may be produced.</p>
               <p>To ſhut up all, becauſe the abſolute and moſt commodious reformation of the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, frauds, deceptions, together with the conſtant practices of evill workes, and evill
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:37276:68"/>worke-men doth cry aloud in the eares of Juſtice, and that they may with the ſame facility and obedience anſwer the rules of the Lawes, and the many prudent orders of State, as a Ship doth the commanding Checques of the Rudder, (as hath been ſaid) It is humbly propoſed, that a well formed Commiſſion, comprehending all the branches of Trades incident to Clothing, and entruſted in the hands of perſons ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, judicious, and conſcientious, conferring with the ableſt and honeſteſt Clothiers, and amongſt them all eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a competent to diſcharge the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Officers, Deputies, and Servants, as in the Cuſtoms, Exciſes, and the like vaſt employments is done, will be found a true and moſt ſerviceable Rudder to this Ship of richeſt Fraight, which the whole world can produce; For nothing doth more prejudice the publique utility, then that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhould exerciſe his own fancy, nor is any thing a greater Bane to a well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned Common-wealth, then ill gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and diſorderly Trade.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Civitais everſio, morum, non murorum caſus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:37276:69"/>
            <head>Poſt-ſcript,</head>
            <p>SUch is the excellency of the Sheep above all the other irrationall Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as well in his naturall as in his ſymbolicall capacities, that not onely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, but piety it ſelfe may thereby receive inſtruction, even to the recreating the mind and ſoule; and becauſe they may prove ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to deceive the melancholy of ſome mens leiſurable houres, it is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhortly to preſent the courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with ſome meditations, wherein ſhall be ſhewed, that as every part of the ſheep is uſefull in Food, or Clothing, or Phyſick, or Muſique &amp;c. ſo alſo is he divine in his uſes, and comparative conſiderations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37276:69"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
